throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, basher's of
bin cheese. You are listening to the Lord of Spirits
podcast. And my co-host, their very Reverend Doctor,
heptamaster, sextamaster. Did we solve that last time I
can't remember now? It is sex. It is sex cast, which
sounds about there you go, heptaca. Father Steve Indiana
It's with me from Lafayette Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick in a Mayan's Pennsylvania,
atop the Eldridge Tower of Podcasting,
perched above both a gateway to the underworld
and as I have lately learned a neoteric tattoo parlor
and we're live.
And if you are listening to us live,
you can call us at 855-237-2346 and talk to us.
We're gonna get to your calls in the second half of the show.
And guest producer, Bobby Lord of Spirits
This was the name of my acoustic 80s side project band, Maddox.
will be taking your cause.
Speaking of which, did you get kind of deja vu there for a second during the intro?
Yes, I did. I don't know what's going on.
I've just the Christmas time.
I don't know about these orthodox media depot babies.
That's all I don't know.
I'm a little rusty. Come on.
Oh wow, see we didn't even try to call in Bobby.
Here he is on the store already.
That was fast.
Wow.
Anyway, yes.
So, a word from our sponsor. This episode is sponsored, and this is a different ad you guys,
it's slightly different. Is sponsored by the Orthodox Studies Institute at St. Constantine
College which exists to advance the study and application of Orthodox Christianity in
faithfulness to holy tradition. O.S.I's next live course is Tolkien, God's Monsters and Myth
taught by none other than your humble servant.
What you do
about Tolkien? I know. This class starts on November 12th and runs for five weeks on Tuesday
nights to check out the syllabus and to sign up. Go to orthodoxstudys.org slash LOS. I hope
I see all of you there. So last time on the 100th episode of Lord of Spirits, we board
you for three hours and 53 minutes, a new record. And so in that vein, we are going to continue
on. Picking up where father Steven so graciously saved us.
from having our first four-hour episode, which surely would have become five-hour episode
to be rivaled only by an eventual 24-hour live televon, which he has also threatened to
make come to pass.
That's a problem.
No.
So this is our 101st episode.
So where were we?
I don't remember.
A lot of stuff has happened since that.
It's been two weeks.
Yeah, I know there's been hurricanes and that's great.
It starts with an earthquake, et cetera, et cetera.
It's airplane, yeah.
But Lenny Bruce is not afraid so he's dead so that helps I imagine.
Yeah, so we were on sort of on the verge of talking about modernism.
Yes.
And realizing it was going to be another three hours if we kept going.
Yes, it's a modernism in its various and sundry foe forms, including post.
is gonna be our subject this evening.
Yeah.
But we're going to break with tradition and actually start talking about it in the first half.
What?
I know.
We have a hundred episode tradition of not doing that ever, but there was that episode we
did backwards.
We're scoff laws, even the laws that we make ourselves.
I've got to keep it fresh.
Yeah.
I've got to keep myself entertained at least, even if I'm not entertaining anyone else.
So yeah, sort of quick review.
Kind of catches up in terms of what we talked about last time because I imagine most of our current listeners whether live or later will not be listening to this immediately after concluding that four hour.
No, there are no.
And even then they may have gotten diverted in their thinking by the calls at the end and...
you know, a certain man of 1000 heresies calling into ask me questions about twin peaks.
So to get everybody back, back on the same page, a very short version of what we were talking about
last time was talking about how do you compare Christianity and other things? To be more specific.
Yeah, right. It was a question of we had talked about in the episode before.
that even the idea of a sort of continuity of the worship of the true God, the true worship of the
true God, starting with the beginnings of humanity. Yeah, that literally it's the same religion,
it's the same religion at the beginning as Orthodox Christianity now. Yeah. So you know,
a nuanced and fair claim.
But so within that, that of course,
there are a bunch of obvious questions about that, right? Because obviously what hunter-gatherers
in the Neolithic era did that we would now retroactively label as religious practice, is not
identical to, say, the Sunday to find liturgy in an Orthodox church. Right. Right. Right.
So what does it mean, then, that if we're going to claim that those things are fundamentally the same?
in being the true worship of the true God.
Yeah, that's basically what we talked about last year.
So it was a question of how do we recognize
Continues and discontinuities and how much discontinuity do you need
with sort of the flow of Christianity and the Christian tradition
before you're out now outside of it.
Right.
How do we separate sort of an adaptation to changing a way of life?
Right. So, for example, you know, human civilization has urbanized over the past several centuries.
We don't primarily live in farming villages anymore.
At least most of our listeners say speak for yourself, father. Yeah, most of our listeners today don't even farming villages. You live in a swamp.
They live in a city of some size, right or some kind, right?
And that has a different economic structure than those agricultural farming.
villages did and the all kinds of things have changed. And so the church, right,
Orthodox Christianity has adapted to those things, right? We have parking lots.
They didn't have parking lots at the village church, right? We have, right? So
there are adaptations and you can point at those and say, well, that's a
difference. Therefore, that's a change. You didn't used to have parking lots. Now
you have parking lots. See your religion is not in changing. Your religion has
changed. Right.
And we would look at that and say, well, okay, that's kind of silly.
Right.
That's not a substantial change.
That's just an adaptation to life in a new context.
But there are other things that we could do hypothetically, right?
If all of a sudden I tore down the iconostasis and put a rock band in the sanctuary around
the altar where you would look at that and say, okay, that's not orthodox.
Christianity anymore
That's something else. It may be some other type of Christianity, but it's something. It's not orthodox Christianity anymore
right
And there are things I could do where you would point out and say okay, that's not even Christianity anymore
Right like I started putting up statues of Zeus and Athena and stuff like in the church with the icons
Right you would say okay, that's not even Christianity anymore
Now you're in some kind of paganism.
Right. You were shaping a different God. Yeah. So we were talking about those differences,
right, to kind of give an idea of what is a change in an adaptation? What is a break with tradition?
Right. What is transformative? And so we talked about what we were talking about other groups that
have, so for example, Christian elements or things about them.
that might look Christian, right, the outside.
And the examples we used last time were
nosticism and neoclatinism, right?
Those things, so there are sort of Christian elements,
right? So nostics will talk about a redeemer,
or they'll talk about a Christ.
Even the salvation maybe.
Yeah, they'll talk about salvation.
They'll talk about a creator God.
That's not the way they like, but.
They're happy about what?
Right. So there are these terms, right? These things and people use, and it's not incorrect
to refer to Christian narcissism over against other forms of narcissism, meaning forms of
narcissism that have these Christian trappings versus some other ones. So there are forms of
narcissism, for example, where the redeemer figure isn't Christ at turkulas. Yeah. Okay. Well, if your
your D-Refingers Hercules.
There's not even a pretense to Christianity.
Right.
You're firmly within the Greek pagan world.
And so we pointed out we were using three sort of things
as our benchmarks.
We talked about how in the early church,
Christian churches are encountering these other groups
in other cities and other towns and other places.
and they're trying to determine, okay?
Okay, this other group that's meeting this other town,
are they a group of Christians like us,
or are they doing something else?
Right, and it wasn't just like,
well, they identify as Christians, so okay, they're Christians.
Right, there was actually,
do we have certain things in common?
And the three we were using,
particular to those groups were their view of,
well, whether they had and what scriptures they had.
Yeah.
Right. What authority structures they had within their group and what their view was of the creation
in the material world. Then also what their way of life was, sort of ethical and moral considerations.
Right. And in the case of narcissism and neoplatonism, as much as they had trappings of Christianity,
in both cases deliberately.
Right?
they really consisted mostly of things foreign to Christianity, foreign elements to Christianity.
So they had different scriptures, they had different authority structures, they had radically
different views of the material world, they practiced a different way of life.
And so the Christian groups that encountered them and Sadie or Neas for example writing
for those Christian groups said, no, you're not one of you guys are not part of us, you're
not one of us.
you're doing something different.
Right.
And we talked about how there's a certain sort of
artificiality to it that as I mentioned, those Christian elements were in
neoplatonism and were in narcissism deliberately.
Yeah, they were sort of constructed.
Someone's like, I have a good idea and let's, you know, put these things together.
It wasn't something that was revealed, you know, or grew up within a community.
anything like that. It was yeah yeah to either incorporate what they thought were
interesting Christian ideas or to appeal to the people that Christianity was
appealing to in the case of Neoplatonism and trying to win them back. It was a
deliberate and therefore kind of artificial thing. And we we compared that to
right not like noticism and Neoplatonism to a false Christianity. And the example
we used of a false Christianity was Aryanism.
Yeah.
Right.
Where the Aryan's-
Obviously, Council of Dicev very clear, they're not Christians because they believe in a different Christ.
Right.
But if you look at those elements I named, they were using the same scriptures.
They had the same authority structures. Right. There were Aryan bishops.
They had the same roughly view of the material world as Christians did.
And they practiced rough...
the same way of life, morally and ethically, right? They had the Eucharist, they had a liturgy,
right? And so that was rather than being something other than Christian, that was a false Christianity.
Yeah, and they're, you know, they're canonically treated differently than non-Christians.
Right. And so that's why I like to say Basil, a great for example, would receive them
into the church without baptism, whereas a gnostic.
or a neoplateness he absolutely would baptize,
right in every case.
Yep, right, because those are something different.
This is just somebody who's part of a false Christian body.
So, where we were headed after that,
was we were going to, and this was way too much
to do in what episode we determined,
as we stretched into our third hour.
Yeah.
That's that.
Let's use this kind of framework and understanding to take a look at the relationship between Christianity and modernism.
Yeah, and this is not easy because modernism is not a religion. It's not a group, it's not a church, it's not a...
Yeah, but I mean, there's not like an organization that you can point to and say, okay, this group, these group, this group is the church of modernism.
and they do, you know, like, it's not like that.
Yeah, it's really at some points. Oh, yes, of course. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah. I mean, they did put up statues of reason after the French Revolution. You can argue free masons are. Yeah. Oh, no, free masons.
But yeah, but there's not it's it's not, you know, in some ways, the challenge is different because then then then challenges in the past where there's clear groups to kind of
argue with and compare yourself against so for this these are cultural movements
that that's dear whole societies often without those societies really being aware of it
Especially as it gets a generation or two on
Their ideologies. Yeah, yeah, and as we've talked about before and we'll talk about again tonight
What you're talking about an ideology what we're really talking about is a spirit
Yeah, there is a spirit that is motivating this
And if it's a spirit that's not the Holy Spirit,
that it's not the Holy Spirit.
Right.
And so that makes it kind of a foreign thing.
But before we can really get into modernism and its relationship to Christianity, we have
to talk about what modernism even is.
Yeah, because that word gets used.
I mean, most people when they say the word modern, they just mean, you know, the now times.
Yeah.
But there's also even modernism itself as anism.
right, gets thrown around a lot as a slur, right? Like the way liberal gets thrown
around as a slur now. Like liberal used to, and we're going to use it tonight, but it
used to actually mean something like if someone was liberal, they believed in certain things.
Yeah. But now it's just like, you know, you're liberal. We're going to talk later about
how the fact that words like Marxist and fascist now get thrown around all the time. Like Marxist
is anyone to my left fascist is
anyone to my right, you know, they just become slurs. Like they're not meaningful words
anymore. Like awesome. It's like a cuss word, right? Like yeah. We're calling someone a jerk,
you know, like it doesn't actually tell you anything about the person. If I say that they're
a jerk, you just say, Oh, why don't you like them? He is bad. I don't think it doesn't convey
And so modernism is the same thing, right?
And so like you hear modernism just used to refer to anything recent, right?
Yeah.
Anything newfangled is just modernism.
I get that out of here.
Right.
Uh, did they have that 19th century Russia?
No, it's modernism.
Right.
Um, and they have modernism in 19th century Russia.
No, it was better for it.
And so again, with the slur thing, modernism is not just things you don't like.
Right.
And it's not things that aren't quote unquote,
patristic, meaning there aren't these two categories,
patristic and modernist, into which all things fall.
And there's a certain irony about the way those are juxtaposed,
because the whole idea of
of patristic and patristics and the
theopatristic movement and all of
that is is a modern movement.
Yeah, doesn't doesn't necessarily
mean that everything it says or does
or is as bad, but it is a reality
of the modern world. It's resource
it's resource mod. It's ad fontis.
Yeah, the original sources. There's
nothing wrong with reading the
original sources. You should read
the original right, right?
Exactly. Right. But it's just the
is that move is a modern move. Yeah, just historically and philosophically.
And therefore, trying to oppose modernism and quote-unquote,
patristic, whatever, patristic thinking, patristic, this, patristic that, is a very modern way of
looking at things, right? And modernism is not thing, something that you know,
somebody uses certain trigger words in their description.
I couldn't get the name the name if I wanted to.
So this person will remain anonymous if they're still out there listening.
But in the very early days of this show, low those many four years ago, I used the word
dialectic in an episode.
And this is back when I was still on the Facebooks.
Before blessed I escaped.
And somebody who had listened to that episode was very upset.
It posted something on the order of, what do you mean by dialectic?
And sort of a rant about Hagel and sood.
Yeah.
And my response, of course, to molify him was to just say communism.
Right.
But, you know, we can all, no matter where you stand on anything, right?
is working.
that'll trigger you, right? Like, you know, someone saying Picard is better than Kirk,
you'll get it year full for me. I will be triggered.
You'll hear me mock a man who played a Frenchman with a British accent for half his life. Anyway,
you know, he was younger. He was younger. I think I pointed this out recently. He was younger when
he started that show than you and I both are now by just two years. Yeah. He looked a lot older
though. I know. I know. I know.
Hold and kind of weathered.
I know. Anyway, um, not sort of robust like William
Shatter. Anyway.
See, I got triggered right there.
Talking about. Um, yeah.
And but so, you know, things that use certain buzzwords.
Right. Like just because someone says dialectic.
Uh, just because someone says, you know, uses a term drawn
on from the social sciences or something that doesn't mean
whatever the
they're saying is automatically modernism, right?
Yeah.
So what is it?
Well, nobody comes out and says, hey, I'm a modernist.
Yeah, not anymore, I don't think.
And here's our modernist manifesto, right?
So like, with our planks.
But there are certain things that we could talk about
that are elements, that are views that emerge
starting in the early modern period,
that sort of
to what modernism is. The first one of the clearest ones is an emphasis on the individual.
Yeah, that's probably the most foundational of all of this stuff.
Yeah, because everything else is dependent on this. And what we mean by
individual is exactly what that term means. Individual, autos, right, cannot be divided.
right so it is the sort of the basic unit of humans is one
right? So, but in describing that cannot be divided, that means it's what we
arrive at when we divide that person from everything. So the individual, the
difference between the idea of an individual and a human person, for example, is
that the idea of a person as an individual is that you are looking at them
separated from all of their relationships, all their social relationships, family
relationships.
community relationships, religious connections, right?
You abstract all of that.
And when you abstract the visual,
you arrive at the individual.
Yeah, and that then gives rise to this question of,
who am I?
What do you get?
Which seems like, we're so inculcated with this idea
that we think that that is the universal question
that every human has ever asked himself.
But it's kinda not.
No, no. And when you combine that as happened in Western Europe, for example, with a bad
case of Plato brain, then you think that yourself is this sort of set thing, right? You're
sold within you. And so you get people wanting to go out and find them. So I'm going to go
find myself. Yeah, you're this irreducible thing. I need to figure out who I am.
Rather than seeing who I am as well, I am the husband of my wife.
I am the pastor of my parish.
I am the son of my mother.
I am the brother of my sisters.
All those of relationships that are predicated upon someone else.
All these connections are what make me me.
No, we got to figure it out, abstracted from everything else.
And with that, of course, also comes...
the idea that human persons are basically impermeable.
Right.
You know, yeah, this is why this is why the the news concept is so hard
from modern people to grasp that it's you know, that that
thoughts come in from the outside and are received by the news.
It's because we don't think of thoughts being that way.
You know, yeah.
And so then taking the next step from this, you arrive at a kind
of egalitarianism.
Hmm, right.
meaning if we're talking about individuals abstracted from all of these relationships,
then they're all kind of not just equal, but the same. Right? You say, well, okay,
this person is rich, and this person is poor, but no, no, no, no, we're abstracting them
from those relationships. Right? Two infants, right? Separated from their families.
Thank you.
put in a room, right? Or two dead bodies, right? Like where we've we've abstracted them from
everything. And so now they're basically the same. Yeah. This is why in was it is that the
Declaration of Independence or that I can remember with the Declaration of Independence or Constitution
of the United States, it says, you know, we hold these truths to be self-evident that all men are
created equal.
That's decorative independence.
Yeah, decoration independence, which...
I mean, that is got to be one of the biggest gas lightings, gas lightings in history.
Well, they didn't say just all men.
I mean, you know, males, they meant humans.
Yeah, that's spec when men, that's spec when men did not just mean men.
Yeah.
Yeah, because I mean, it's obvious.
It's obvious, like if anyone's ever seen the two of us together,
Like we're both tall individuals but
But if you and I were to have a wrestling match, it is clear that we are not created equal.
There is no question that you would win because I do not know any kind of special martial
arts where I could defeat someone who is six times my size or whatever.
Whatever a human like me compared to a hill like you is.
The elbow.
That's right.
Yeah, we're not created equal.
We're just not.
Right.
But so you're no good.
And I'm just a dude from their perspective, right?
All inequalities and even all differences are acquired, right?
Yeah.
In the modern point of view, right?
Think we're so, right?
Think John Locke's, right?
Tabularasa, right?
So any differences are just historicized, right?
Well, this person happens to be rich and
that person happens to be poor because by happenstance,
they were born into the families they were.
Right, but there is no difference between them at all
as people, right?
Everything, everything that separates people
is just the vicissitudes of history.
Yeah.
It is all kind of accidental.
Yeah, I mean, they're reacting against the idea
that some people are,
You know, this sort of pagan idea, right, that that the elite are just better as appointed by the gods.
Better people. Yeah, just better people. Right. Yeah. If you're stronger, you're better, you know,
whatever, their reaction gets that idea. But they're going in the other direction. Yeah. Right. Yeah.
It's like, oh, well, this person is physically stronger than that person. Well, they were able to
work out and exercise that they didn't have to this or they worked this kind of job as opposed to
So that kind of, right, so it's all just historicized with
which means that if you can re-engineer that, you can completely transform people.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, you get the subsequent idea then of equal treatment under the law, which is not the
same thing as egalitarianism, but you don't really get equal treatment under the law without
egalitarianism, really.
It's not to be confused with God being
no respecter of persons, this is something else.
Right, right. This is something else. Right. Because for example, right, sure, that works
with God being no respecter of persons. But how does that work with state Paul telling
us we have different gifts and different callings? Yeah. Right. This says that's not true.
Right. That's just accidental. Right.
and not related to the person, right, at all.
This then leads to,
step one is democracy, right?
But ultimately comes to full flower in Jacksonian democracy,
right, which is,
for those of you who don't know a lot of American history,
Andrew Jackson expanded the franchise to all males.
The franchise being voting.
That's as I continued.
use antiquated terms. Oh, literally, it means making them French. Yeah. But so it allowed
them all to vote, which was seen by the previous Vatican, but there's a horrific idea because
of course all those pores are the mob out there. Right. Yeah. But that democratization,
course goes further, ultimately, because it becomes
the claim that because everybody is really the same other than these vicissitudes of history,
then everyone's opinion is of equal value.
Right.
One man, one vote.
Yeah, and I mean, and that's, you know, that's why everyone says things like, well, everyone
is entitled to his opinion.
And why there's, you get this idea on the internet like, if you, if you delete someone's
comments that that's kind of some sort of moral
wrong because of course everyone's comments are of equal value.
Right.
Right. And so yeah, if we're going to build a road,
we should take a vote on how to build it.
Hopefully after listening to an engineer,
but not necessarily.
Yeah.
Because that engineer also only gets one vote
even though he knows way more about the subject.
Right.
You also get a
the idea of the pursuit of enjoyment. That's not what the pursuit of happiness meant in the Declaration of Independence.
That was a sub-in for property. That was the right to pursue wealth. Yeah, but but the idea of the pursuit of enjoyment, the idea of leisure.
And this really kicks in with...
realization. Yeah, where you have the idea of a working day, right? And then your free time that you
could do with it what you want. Right. But it's already starting in the modern period. And so you
start to see, you know, theater, for example, originally comes out of religious ritual. Yeah.
Yeah. And maintains these ritual elements of these kind of things like say in Athens. By the time
you get to Shakespeare, the 17th century.
right? You're now at the realm of popular entertainment. There are groundlings.
Yeah, it's it's for fun. Right. And yeah, and there's money to be made. Yes.
And so this goes for being this kind of communal religious event or communal
quasi-religious bonding exercise to being entertainment. I have to say, by the way,
as someone who, you know, you think about the Roman Empire in a daily basis, but I
Think about William Shakespeare on a daily basis.
And it's funny to me though, like as you said, when he was doing his thing in late 16th or
early 17th century, that was that was popular entertainment.
You know, that was the stuff that people went outside the city.
You know, it was that was low, that was low entertainment.
Yeah.
It's so funny that people think of Shakespeare now as being, you know, super hoidy, toyty,
high stuff.
I think that's mostly American.
Yeah, maybe I don't know. Maybe Sir Ian McHellen said that the Royal Shakespeare Company is basically welfare for out of work British actors. Wow. Is that another sought at Patrick Stewart? Yes.
I knew it.
I didn't think that Patrick Stewart would be our whipping boy for this episode, but here we are.
Here we are. There we are.
So, so another element that you find within modernism are theories of development, right?
Meaning, as we just said, there's this deep view of egalitarianism and this historicization
of differences, right, and hierarchies.
And so that means a theory of development is, okay, well, how did we arrive at these
hierarchies. Right. What is the historical process by which things came to be the way they are?
With the idea that if we can understand that and again, modernism, especially once you get
into the 19th century and Germany is treating history as vissen shaft as a science, right? We can
determine these laws and we can then steer it to go away that we think would be better.
Yeah, and there's nothing wrong with society that can't be
secured by progress.
You know, the inexorable march towards things getting better,
you know, we're so much better off, we are so much better and better off,
because those two things always go together than people in the past, you know.
Right. And exhibit A of this is Karl Marx.
Karl Marx is peak modernism. Right.
He's he's
he and his friend Abraham Lincoln, but we'll go to that another time.
Carl Brown rocks tonight is is peak watered as him.
Because what does he do?
Well, he goes historically, I know, okay, here's the move from primitive communism.
Yeah.
Right.
Imperialism, feudalism.
And now the beginnings of capitalism, right.
Here is how these different social classes have been formed.
and transformed, how they war against each other,
struggle against each other, right,
over the course of history.
And so now we've arrived at capitalism and we're here,
right?
And one of the things people don't understand
about Marx is that he thought capitalism
was the second best idea anybody ever had.
That's right.
Yes.
He thought capitalism was great,
but not the end all be all, right?
Now we move up to this even higher stage.
Yeah, for him, the weighted.
do that now that we've diagnosed now that we followed through how all this has happened
in the past.
Now we're going to grab the reins of this and we're going to steer it to where we want
it.
Yeah.
And, and if you're not headed in that direction, then you are not on, and this is a very
common phrase you hear now, you're not on the right side of history.
Right.
That's this idea that there's this move for and, and, you know, very commonly, we will
say things like, I can't believe that here in 2024, blah, blah, blah.
Someone is saying, got it out of the eye.
Yeah, you know, it's like it's it's current year.
How could this be happening?
Yes. Yeah.
Although I will say I recently went back and watched one of the best television programs
of the 90s and I was amazed at what you could say on network TV in the 90s.
Hmm. Oh, it's true.
Like stuff you couldn't even say on Twitter today without getting canceled.
Yeah.
We're saying like that.
I mean, even just 15 years ago, like, yeah.
Like I would just say, you know, go, go watch the office, which ended what in 2012.
Yeah.
I mean, yeah, that that whole show practically is, is cancelable.
These days.
So this can change pretty fast.
But yeah.
But so that also then this idea of development also gives you the kind of chronological
arrogance and snobbery that we've talked about that are 19th century German
friends are so representative in love.
And certain.
20th and 21st century Americans.
That's love.
We now just stand at the pinnacle.
Where the greatest country in the history of the world.
We're a super modernist thing to say, you guys.
Everything has been leading to us here now.
We are the pinnacle right of of all of human achievement culture and society
throughout here.
That's why all biblical prophecy points in America.
Yeah.
No biblical prophecy points at Guam.
Edward 19th Century German Lutheranism.
about that.
And we get super mad in other countries when they won't recognize the America is the greatest
country in history.
Like exopias, hello.
So yeah.
So I mean, I love my country, but so if that's, I love the country of Louisiana.
Anyway.
The uh...
But if that's sort of a broad sketch, those are elements at least of modernism, right?
So let that suffice at least for this evening because we don't want to go four hours again
as sort of a rough sketch of the outlines of modernism.
Where and how do we see that working its way into Christianity?
Yeah, and it's probably worth at least mentioning that even though we kind of...
level a few criticisms along the way. We're not saying that none of what
Modernism talks about or says or thinks about that none of it is true in any way.
You know, yeah, we're just kind of this is none of it. Yeah, this is this is it's it's deal
Yeah, I think that 19th century Germany was the pinnacle of human civilization is bunkum
But you know, that is definitely not true
You did get Grim's fairy tales and that was not
So how do we see modernism and Christianity and is modernist Christianity in danger of
becoming not just a false Christianity but something else, something other than Christianity?
Right, in the way that we were talking about before because modernism as such is a foreign
an element.
to Christianity. Modernism did not emerge out of Christianity.
Modernity and modernism arose out of a, frankly, to be totally blunt out of a rejection of Christianity.
Hmm. Yeah.
Out of an attempt to find a basis for civilization apart from the Christian religion in Western Europe.
Yeah, I mean, in a lot of ways, it's a kind of ideological tower of Babel.
Yeah. And everywhere where modernism is taken hold, right, it causes a revolution.
That revolution is always the anti-Christian.
Yep. See France. See Russia.
So it is a foreign element, it is a verse.
And so with Christianity gets resh-
by a foreign element, that's where we start moving into the territory of okay
this is something else. This isn't just a false form of Christianity. This is
something other than Christianity. Right. So you could very easily see how
Christianity, we're in the United States so we're looking at it here but I
I imagine other people in other countries.
of Western European origin or connection or cultural tradition.
May see this too, how Christianity has gotten reshaped
around individualism, around entertainment,
restructured, and sort of democratic way, right?
And as thereby become this sort of very artificial thing,
This very constructed thing.
Right. People come and write new progressive creeds.
Yes. Oh, they're horrible too. Right. These are not creeds that emerge out of the
lived experience of a group of religious people. This is someone deliberately trying to
write a new progressive creed. Yeah, like I've got an idea. Right. It is artificial or
rewritten versions of the art father also very often. Yeah. That's, or innovative worship
styles or elements.
And here's the problem.
We're going to get into this more in the third half.
But the response to this, the sort of tradd response, right?
The traditionalist response, which is not the same as the response of tradition,
but the traditionalist response, has basically just been the flip side of the same coin.
So while the modernist wants to reconstruct Christianity according to the tenets of modernism,
the traditionalist wants to reconstruct Christianity in terms of their own personal view of the
tradition.
Yeah, with no one else having to say over what they think.
Unless they could claim the majority and then they appealed to democracy.
Yeah. Yeah.
Which again, right?
So it's, it's just as modern.
Right.
It's just as much as a modernist approach.
It's just a preference that looks
aesthetically more traditional.
Right.
But it's not actually part of the tradition.
It's just as artificial.
It's just as much of a reconstruction.
and ultimately just as
modernist. Right. And we see that in these groups where Christianity has been reshaped by
modern trends, you see, for example, that egalitarianism expressed in sexuality, in who they ordained,
which is just about anybody, because everybody's the same. Remember? That's. And as we talked about,
Right.
You look at the
these areas, right? How does modernism affect the ethical way of life? It becomes different,
a different way of life, a different way of life, practice by Christianity, right? Scriptures
become a very different thing. Worship becomes a very different thing. The view of the world
is very different.
They actually have a more positive
of his view of the material created world, then Christianity has helped. So it's sort of
the opposite problem of narcissism, narcissism of course, that the whole world out there
is all evil. Right. This is bad and you should stay away from it. Whereas they say it's
all good and untainted by any sin. Yeah. The denial of fallenness. Yeah. Right. The noble
savage, right? We're so again, right? So, you know, so again.
And on these criteria we're using, it's a different religion.
And as we mentioned, there's a difference between the tradition and traditionalism.
Tradition is something which forms and is formed in a community living together and sharing
a common life.
is an individual person's ideology or preferences or view.
Yeah, I really like in his little book, which was, I think, a lecture originally by
Yaroslav Pelikan called the vindication of tradition. He has a very famous saying that tradition
is the living faith of the dead, whereas traditionalism is the dead faith of the living. I always
love a good chiasmus. But I mean, it's a good shorthand, right? Because tradition is something you
you become part of it.
where as traditionalism is a thing you can struct.
It really is.
I'm triggered by chiasms, by the way.
That was a kid I used to get hit and then kicked and then kicked and then hit.
No, yeah, I can see that.
But I think, you know, and the thing is, of course, that traditionalism
thinks that it's, or claims that it's simply being traditional.
All right.
But, but that, I mean, but if you look at people that are living within the tradition,
that is not how they actually function.
Right.
There is an externality to living within a tradition.
It's about how you relate to other people, right?
And the life that you share, the public life, uh,
whereas traditionalism is an internal thing because it's about my
intro-proversies and my own individual practices.
Right.
And I want to live.
And you know, does this place line up to what I think?
if not, I'm leaving and going finally one that does.
Yeah, and if we're talking about our modern ideas, right?
Liberté, egalité, fraterité, right?
That liberté, right, is this is how I want to live, right?
I want to live a traditional way of life, and I should be free to live that way, right?
That's very modern.
Yeah.
Right.
It's kind of inescapable now, understandably, but like, but this is modernism.
I mean it just...
is. Right. So there's a difference between Christianity existing in modern times and
modernist Christianity. Because one can practice and be a part of and live within and live
out the Christian tradition against any cultural backdrop.
Modernist, feudalism, whatever.
Right. The question is what makes modernist Christianity, modernist Christianity is that it has been reshaped by modernism. The Christianity has been changed by these foreign elements.
Right. So here's an example of the difference.
Okay.
Once you get the printing press
In the early modern period you have the proliferation of books.
and of texts, which leads to a huge rise in literacy rates, especially thanks to Protestantism.
Yeah, I mean, it's transformative of society and the world.
Right.
Okay.
Now, the fact that, now that, that is a kind of egalitarianism.
That is a kind of evening of the bar.
It is no longer only the educated upper classes who can read and who have access to books
and texts and the Bible, right?
Now that has been made available to the common man, right? And that is a modern thing.
But we're not saying that's a bad thing in and of itself, right? Where does it cross the line
from being Christianity within modernity over into modernist Christianity? Well Christianity within
modernity is we now all have access to the scriptures. We read the scriptures devotionally. We study
the scriptures we learn from the scriptures, right? But we do that within the
You can't...
of a tradition that puts boundaries on our interpretations that can correct us.
Yeah. Right. They could tell us we're wrong. Whereas within modernist Christianity,
right, each one of those people gets a vote as to what the text means.
Yeah. What everybody thinks is the same. You know, like, like, yeah, I've heard, I've heard
of Bible studies that follow these lines as being simply the pooling of ignorance.
Yeah.
Well, there's a, there's a, there's a really insidious way this works out too, right?
Because you'll get this most scholars agree. Yeah.
As if that's how we decide what is true, we get all the smart people who have studied this to all
vote. Right. And then boom, there we go. Right. That's truth. Yeah, I mean, areas could have said that.
Yes, but at one point that was
That was true.
The majority of the church, as it says,
Woken grown to find itself Aryan.
Most scholars agree that Aryanism is true.
Yeah.
That's where you're moving into modernism.
Right, where you think truth is decided
by a sort of majority vote, right?
Or for example, you can have
a beautiful church building constructed
using modern construction.
methods. Yeah, right? Completely modern construction methods,
prefab elements, right, the whole shot, concrete, done 50 years ago,
right? Air conditioners, the newest, right? And use it to conduct
traditional worship, right? Worship that arises from within the
Christian tradition, true worship of the true God, right? You
don't have to have like a wood church built with
by hand, by the parishioners in order to do that, right?
There's nothing evil about those construction methods, right?
But if you allow that, it's not even evil to have, like, say, a microphone so that the people
at the back of the church can hear what's going on.
I don't know.
I don't know, Father.
I don't personally have one.
But, right, because I'm loud.
But you know that there are, I was
informed by a Greek Orthodox bishop that there are prayers for putting the microphone on
when you're about to conduct liturgy. And the one that you use on Sunday is
their voice is going out into all the earth. And then the one that you put on for a weekday is
the voice of one crying in the wilderness. I declined to comment for the story since it was a
I mean, not my bishop, but still a bit.
Right.
But on the other hand, if those modern construction elements,
those other elements are used to reshape your worship.
Right.
If you redesign the sanctuary and the nave,
right, of the church, right.
And into a fundamentally different design that communicates fundamentally different,
say modern things to people.
right? If you have everyone sitting in a circle, right? If you, right? That has now changed
what's going on inside the building. Or you make it shaped like a theater. Yeah. Right?
That has now changed what's going on in the building. Right? And so there is when we're
talking about not just technological development, but technology is a good
place to talk about this, but this kind of development, cultural development in general,
right?
Like the novel is called the novel because it was invented relatively recently.
Because it was new, yeah.
Right.
But nobody's like, you shouldn't read novels, they're modernists, right?
Because I knew.
Yeah.
Right.
So technology here, we're speaking very broadly, right?
Yeah.
The development of these things.
There are sort of two extremes.
You can go to the one extreme where you just everything new that comes along.
is from God and is wonderful and we should just embrace it.
Yeah, this is where you get, you know, some churches now have an online campus of
the church. Yes. I'm sure there's somebody conducting worship in a
Twitter space or something. Right. Yeah, it's a thing. Well, the conducting sums
around and give a big hug to any kind of development that comes out of anywhere.
It's all progress. It's all good. On the other extreme, you have just every
You develop.
and every new technology is evil and from the devil, right?
Yeah, like, yeah, there's the one.
The one I view, yeah.
Which, I mean, you know, I'm number one,
I'm disappointed that the word is not
ludditism or ludditism.
It turns out it's luddism, which I don't know.
That sounds, I don't like it.
The guy's name was Ludd.
I know, I know.
But anyway.
But yeah, like.
No one's a true Luddite like really anti-all technology like as soon as you pick up a rock to do something with it
Yes, that's you you did a technology if you're gonna be an Ann Prem you have to leave the rock on the ground
That's right. You can't pick up rest
Yeah, but it's other said arbitrary point where you cut things off. Yeah, but between those two there is
is using wisdom and ethical considerations surrounding
technology to figure out how to best implement it. There are some developments that are negative
developments that are actually bad and are actually from the devil. There are some developments
in things that are the good gifts of God. But most developments that come from the human
mind like a microwave oven is neither. Yeah, you could do good things with it. You could
do evil things in it. No. You could use a ticac food, you could use it to torch your cats, right?
like one of these is good one is bad.
Hopefully hardly seniors know which is what.
If not, talk to your local Orthodox priest.
Maybe a therapist as well.
Yeah.
Right.
And so to sort of finish up this first half, right?
Coming back to something we've talked about before several times on the show.
You
this is also part of our segue into the second half, where we're going to talk about postmodernism.
And that is that we think about one of the early uses of modernism and especially modernism
as spoken of negatively vis-à-vis Christianity.
It goes back to the fundamentalist versus modernist debates of the early 20th century.
Yeah
which were Presbyterian.
Right.
The fundamentalists called themselves that
because they believed in the fundamentals
of the Christian faith, which were published
in a set of books called The Fundamentals.
Right?
These were things like the Holy Trinity,
the Virgin birth, right?
These are, believe it, the modernists were of course
modernists, right?
That's, and most of them in the early 19th century
the US had been educated.
in the 19th century in Germany.
So they had imbibed deeply for the well of modernism.
And there's this conflict.
But as we've talked about before,
I'll show this is just an apparent conflict.
Because ultimately the fundamentalists,
who later called themselves evangelical fundamentalists
and then fundamentalists became a slur,
and so it just became evangelicals,
Um, um, were.
just as modernist as their opponents. So the example we've given before can
ham as a prime example of a modernist. Yes. Right. So the modernist says, science
proves that God didn't create the world. Yeah. And whereas the fundamentalist
says science proves that God created the world. That God did create the world.
Yeah, yeah, right.
That's not different. Those are equally modernists because what is adjudicating is modern science.
Yeah. Yeah. Science, you're agreeing with the basic presupposition of modernism that science and math
can are the sources of truth, you know, potentially the sole sources of truth.
You're just trying to use the same methodology to arrive at the opposite conclusions.
And you can extend that not just to create it but to the flood, to the exit
to the date of the Exodus, to the, no, no, no, no, we're going to find the scientific
archaeological proof.
Because that's how you prove something is real and true.
Right?
So this is a point to a danger that we're going to return to in the third half of going
to worry its monsters and becoming one yourself.
becoming the thing you hate.
Yes.
It's sort of in pursuit and tilty,
you had no, you know,
becoming one yourself.
But first we need to talk about,
not post-molone,
but post-modernism.
All right, well with that,
we wrap up the first half
of this episode of Lord of Spirits,
so we're going to take a quick break
and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak
and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the
next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation of
the epistles of St. Paul, disconnected from any historical reality.
Paul operated during his entire life as a f***.
faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish world.
In St. Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations,
Father Stephen D. Young surveys Paul's life in writings,
interpreting them within the holy tradition
of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by D. Young's interpretive translation
of St. Paul's epistles, which deliberately avoids
overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in first century Judaism,
The young hopes to unsettle, commonly held notion.
and help the reader reassess Saint Paul
in his historical context.
Available now at store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
Hey, welcome back. It's the second half of this one hundred first episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast. We're talking about modernism and the modern modern to love them.
Yeah, so we actually have some some calls for what we had for a second there. I guess we lost them.
I don't know.
The screen was lighting up and then it went black.
I, you know.
Someone someone's like I have a night no no no
Do you think do you think the Tishka Trudy like bribe him to make her look good?
This is the fix in
My just getting Trudy the tank
I know I know it's hard to top her I mean she's
She's really Bobby to take a dive
It's true. It's true.
Boy, I tell you though, the YouTube chat has been active.
People, all kinds of wacky stuff going on in there.
Someone just says he has NT writes 1600 page study on St. Paul.
Tough read, this commenter says.
The question is, have you read all 1600 of those pages?
Have you read all 1600 of those pages, Father Steven?
Okay, first of all, there was a gentleman's agreement
between all scholars that we were all going to stop after filenement.
So if anybody's claiming they read the whole thing, number one, they're lying and number
two, they're breaking the bro code.
I had no idea there's a biblical scholar's bro code.
How letting us in on the secrets of biblical scholarship.
So all right.
Well, actually look, collars are coming back now.
So we do.
Okay.
Yes, yes, yes, they're back.
They're back.
So we actually have one.
who's phone
at least is from Massachusetts. So hello Yankee. Hello. Hello. Welcome to the Laura Spirits
podcast. Hi. I'm Hannah. I'm actually not from Massachusetts at all. I'm calling
from Nashville, Tennessee. Oh Nashville, Tennessee. It's your your phone number is from
Massachusetts. Is that where you were when you got that cell phone? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Well, those people who keeps calling me about my business loan and saying you need my
personally.
information. Is that why you have a different area code?
You know, now I know, though, that whenever I get phone or whenever I get
collars from Massachusetts, I don't pick up because I know they're all scared.
Exactly that. That's why I still have a West Virginia number.
There you go. Makes it easy.
Yeah. Yeah. I have a Pennsylvania number, of course.
And so because we're we are a crucial swing state, according to all the news
people, I get like multiple political texts every single day.
really it's really irritating yes.
Well remind me to never get a Pennsylvania number.
Yeah well not during an election year anyway.
Yeah right.
Yeah so Hannah from Nashville Tennessee what is on your mind?
What is up?
Well okay so I've been listening to you a couple other podcasts and about angels and demons
and all those things and I know this isn't like directly related to modernism but maybe
a little bit.
I was kind of wondering
do angels and demons have souls like a life force that's like separate from their spirit if that makes sense?
Well short answer no long answer father Steven.
No.
Because the soul is the life of the body.
Right.
Yeah.
And so it is a valid question because
it's a giant beings do every.
certain type of body. Yeah, they have bodies of sorts. Yeah, but they are not a living soul
in the sense that, for example, Adam became a living soul when the breath of life was breathed into him.
Okay. So they don't write. So there isn't a way for them to die in the way that humans die,
right? Like physical death for a human being, the separation of the soul from the body.
Yeah, what would that mean for an angel or a demon?
Right.
So like that can't happen.
of them, but they can die spiritually, right? Meaning spiritual death is what our soul is
separated from God. Right. So an angel or demon can die spiritually, demon in the sense that
its soul can be separated from God, right? It was the source of life. And that's why it's
called death. And so the death, like when Psalm 82 or 81 in the Greek says, you know, you
You have been called gods, it's supposed to be.
but you will die like men. That's what it's talking about.
Yeah.
They will die in that their soul will be separated from the God.
Not that their soul will be separated from their angelic body.
Okay.
That makes sense.
Cool.
I hope you and your little ones are doing well.
They're in Nashville, Tennessee.
Yes, they're... I tried to make them as quiet as possible.
So thank you for taking my questions.
No, we...
I was just gonna quickly say thank you.
I did meet you briefly at the Archdiocese retreat.
I was the one with the,
I was trying to hurt my crazy children in the fellowship hall,
trying to get them out of the way.
I think, I think I know who you are now,
although you've amazed how many people
that descriptor applies to.
Well, that's good.
That makes me feel better about that.
Yes, I mean, yes.
Wherever father Steven goes, children do scatter,
so it's understandable.
Excellent. You should go.
over some time.
It was great.
I love it.
What?
Thanks for calling Hannah.
We're going to take another call.
We have Gregory from Jacksonville.
Gregory, welcome to the Lord's Spirit podcast.
Thank you very much.
Which Jacksonville you're calling from?
The Florida one that Dr. Milton,
that Dr Milton we got a
little bit of rain and. Oh,
I'm safe. Well, that's about it.
Oh, yeah. So big.
From the home of all elite wrestling.
Yeah indeed truly. Wow.
And and the home of live with live with the lows.
One of our other live shows here on
an ancient faith radio that lows are right there in
Jacksonville, Florida. I just get I just get drawn to
these popular shows on this really popular broadcasting station.
I used to go to Father Evans.
and last episode he has brought him up, I'll be like,
no way, man, you're doing the tour.
I have to do a tour.
You're an AFR groupie.
I think you're right.
I get nervous every time I call it, I get really shaky
and my heart beats really fast.
I can go like, wow, I believe this.
We're like the grateful dead now, father Steven.
What are you saying?
Stone?
I don't think so.
It's better than...
the one fish concert, the one fish concert that I worked at when I was a stage
head had a whole lot of unnecessary and I assure you unwanted nudity in amongst
the the the spectators. So yeah.
They say both of us.
Just throwing that out there. So all right, Gregory, what's what's up?
Well, I have a question this time about another sort of modern, I call it
a little different.
I've heard a lot of the weird teachings come out of some evangelical groups about Jesus being
a scene which is predicated by John the Baptist being a scene you know from the Dead Sea Scrolls
and after some really like research I came to understand that well that's not possible
Phil Sofith I mean Jesus preached the resurrection of the Dead it seems didn't believe in that at all
John the Baptist was in the wilderness and he aged well like three until you know his ministry
and this scene's only went out.
every once in a while, they were still a community.
So I was wondering if you may be able to fill me in on if you're aware of this weird new
teaching and maybe some words that you would get to some of the people who teach, you know,
these types of things.
I mean, Father Steven, this is definitely right up your alley.
You know all about the S.E.N.'s.
What I would say to them is stop.
Stop it.
Win it.
I'll get off.
No, well, I would say all those things, but also
So, yeah, it's so, people get excited.
Right. They learn some things about the ancient world
and the world of the Bible and the background
of the New Testament.
And they're cool things that they get excited
about learning them.
And that's natural.
That's not like a bad thing.
And they start making connections
and making connections is sort of fun
and exciting and invigorating and spurs you
on to do more study and things.
but wait
And you're kind of excited in making connections.
There's like a thin line between NT Wright and Charlie Day in front of his cork board
with the strings and the pictures.
And you could very easily fall off the edge of that, right, in the wrong way.
And this is one of those cases, right?
So I mean, even the identification of the Kumaran community.
as Essenes isn't 100% yeah right most scholars would agree on that but as we just said the first half
these things aren't decided by vote they're decided by reality um
a little alone then but then it's like okay well they're out of the desert
say java forators out in the desert right there must be some kind of connection
And part of that gets fuel.
by him trying to remember the name of the scholar. There was an early Roman Catholic scholar who
studied very early on, studied the Dead Sea Scrolls. And when he reconstructed, he did his
reconstruction of the community of Kumaran, and it was like a Benedictine monastery.
Right. And you could tell he's just he's understanding it from his own framework, right? His own,
you know but then that right once that's out there and you're
like, well, you know, say John the four owners kind of this living this proto monastic life,
there's a sort of proto Jewish monastics out there that there's going to be some connection
there, right? And then, you know, they look at some of the sectarian texts in the Dead Sea
Scrolls, and they say, hey, some of this stuff that these texts say, Christ says stuff kind
to like that in the Gospels so that he must be connected to it somehow too.
You know, and then you get the guys who go the farthest who are the guys who are like,
oh, well, there's this teacher of righteousness who they talk about who was actually like the founder,
sort of the leader, founding leader of the Comrade community in like the third century BC.
But especially very early on before all the texts had been read in catalogued and stuff,
you got people going, teacher of righteousness, oh, look, they're talking about him in kind of messianic terms.
I bet that's Jesus.
Yeah.
Right. Even though it's a wrong century.
Right.
.
So it's a lot of sort of excitement and then sort of making too many false connections,
just because things seem similar.
And that is, and frankly, another part of the problem is capitalism in that going out and publishing a book
about the intricate details of community life in Comron is not going to sell a lot of copies
going out selling a book saying that St. John the Baptist hand wrote the Dead Sea Scrolls,
that'll get you on NPR and on the New York type of bestseller list, you know, about your
groundbreaking theory that changes everything about Christianity, you know. So people are
kind of incentivized to take more and more radical positions on that kind of thing in order
to get an audience in order to get money.
So, and it's not just sort of the crude, I want to be famous and make money, but even if you're a legitimate scholar in academic,
you're trying to attract your grant money and stuff, and it's, I need to make my work look important to someone other than me.
You know, and part of being a scholar is sometimes you have to accept that your work is only important to you.
It's true.
Sometimes you're just researching things because you love them and find them interesting
and there's like eight other people on Earth who...
do and maybe you'll meet them at a conference someday and you can talk about it. But otherwise,
right, this isn't going to make you rich and famous and you're even going to struggle
to get grants and get by the way academia works now.
So all of those factors factor in there. But you know, and you see this all the time with
those books, right? Oh, we just found a copy of translating the Gospel of Judas. This
This is gonna change everything up-
Christianity. Did it change anything about Christianity? I mean every Easter time.
No. And every Christmas time. Yeah. Stuff like this always hits the
news with wires. Right. But it always you know, oh, this gospel of Jesus'
wife, right? You know, yeah, these things come out and the people who do them
are motivated by these factors, right? To do them. But you know, either on the
side of buying into them or.
the side of getting this especially worked up. I know people who every time those things
come out at Christmas at Easter, this isn't a tack on Christianity, right, they get all
worked up the other way, right. And it's just like, you know, stand back on it. You did
the right thing by sort of doing a little bit of research and finding out like, oh,
they're jumping to a lot of conclusions and pulling things together that there's no
real evidence of a connection right and that's what you usually find.
with these things. Yeah, I did some light Google searching. When you said that these
people who push these ideas often, they're not always ill-intentioned but they're jumping
from one conclusion to another and they're making connections that are kind of a far fetch.
And I see that as sort of the danger that I've seen with some of the people that I know or care for
that are sort of following this circle that it often leads. But oh well, you know,
That's possible that they also...
like reincarnation so they're trying to tie like something
completely unrelated.
A Google searcher way is like, no,
these things did not believe in reincarnation.
Not even close it.
And then there's like, they get into like earth magic
and power word.
And it just kind of opens this like wormhole of all this.
Really, what you had an episode talking about is magic.
It's like quote unquote, Christian,
that's not really Christian magic.
Yeah.
It's kind of weird.
You know, I wouldn't expect something like that
to lead to such places.
but that's really the motive for my call is just-
knowing like I don't want I want to be able to protect people from that type of technique,
that type of villainous, you know, posing as Christian, you know, demonic activity.
Yeah, that's sort of it's so tieric. Do age slop bucket.
Where that stuff gets thrown. It's just kind of goofy on, I mean, not to, well, it is to be dismissive,
But yeah, like just like take a little deeper people, you know.
I have a little rigor in the way you think.
Fact checking is not all bad.
Sometimes you need to check the facts.
I gotta look at that.
Sorry for distracting from your episode on modernism.
Waiting for this one for quite some time.
I'm really looking forward to where you guys go with this talk on modernism and Christianity and understanding that.
I'm going down to it.
But new AG stuff is modernist, right?
It's this constructed individualist thing.
So yeah, you're not entirely out of our lane.
So thanks very much for calling, Gregory.
Thank you, Father.
All right.
Postmodernism.
What is that?
Yes.
Just anything that happens after modernism, right?
Yeah.
Modernism is over.
does that. Modernism is over. Now we're in postmodernism, you guys.
Yeah. So lots of people use the term postmodernism. Sort of like we had to define modernism,
we kind of have to define postmodernism. Yeah. Because once again, for example, it's not anything you
don't like. I think that's how it was used, like especially like in the early to mid 90s, a lot
then there was a lot of that any societal tread that was bad was postmodern post
Modern. Yeah. Yeah. Um, here's the here's my controversial statement. This is going to alienate a lot of people.
It's not Marxism. Yeah. I mean, Marxism is a modernism. You guys. Yes. It is peak modernism. Okay. So there is no such thing as postmodern Marxism.
I know you hear people talk about it, but it doesn't exist.
It's a married bachelor.
So such a exposed modern Marxism and calling it neo-Marxism doesn't help let me explain why okay
Because here's what happens they say well no it's neo-Marxism because they don't believe xyz
Which are constitutive parts of Marxism
They believe these other things instead. So let's see it's neo-Marxism. Okay
So here's the problem. Let's say I decide right now. I'm going to call father Andrew a neo-fascist
Next.
Father Andrew, you're a neo-fascist.
I'm the new kind of person who believes
in private ownership and government control
of the private means of production.
So, Father Andrew then proceeds to say,
no, I'm not.
And he lays out all the places he disagrees with fascism.
Yes.
And I say to him, aha, that's why you're a neo-fascist.
Yeah.
Because if you take away all your disagreements
with fascism, you're a fascist, right?
So that...
That's not helpful.
Yeah.
Okay.
So I know some very popular people who I may have shared a stage with this year to occasions,
talk about post-order DO-marks is it's not a thing.
Okay.
Now, I'm not saying the phenomenon that people are pointing at when they use that term
doesn't exist.
I'm saying it's not a good label for the phenomenon.
That's not the right word for it.
It's not the right label to put on it.
Right. Because that label doesn't make sense. I understand why they're using that label. Right.
Because calling something postmodern doesn't have any bite to it in our culture. Right.
Referring to critical theory doesn't have any bite in our culture. Refernalizing has to bite in our culture.
But calling somebody a commie has some bite. Right. So we got to work Marxism in there somewhere. Okay. I get it.
but it really has nothing to do with Marxist.
Okay, like it's the same way like just calling a guy upon the on the right wing calling
him a populist that doesn't have a lot of bite in our culture, right?
But you call him a fascist, right?
That that one stings a little more, right?
What we still do using that language isn't helpful because it doesn't actually describe,
right, or define the person.
So yeah, yeah, I mean, I post modernists, all of the big post modernists you've heard
I'm Jacques Derrida.
Shelfuko were also post Marxists.
Yes, right.
And I mean, when I was when I low, when I was an undergrad,
these many decades ago now,
I was my bachelor's degree that I that I completed,
because I have an incomplete bachelor's degree as well.
But the one that I completed was in English literature.
And so I became interested in literary theory,
not because I was interested in literary theory,
but kind of because I sort of hated it
Whenever I encountered it.
I want to understand what was going on, but I read up rather good book that critiques postmodern
literary theory and it's by a guy named Terry Eagleton, who is a Marxist.
He doesn't critique, I mean, it's been a long time throughout the book. I don't think he critiques
it from a Marxist point of view in particular, but that's his deal. He is a modernist.
He has a modern skill of the water discat.
Yeah, yeah, right.
Postmodernism is not anything other than modernism, right?
So just because someone rejects modernism
that doesn't make them a postmodernist.
Right.
And it's not anything that references subjectivity.
Yeah, right.
I will take us back once again to the early days
of this program,
Um, where
we were talking about the importance of subjectivity in terms of our view of the world.
Yeah, right. An hominology, if you want to use that. Right. But,
the album, it's up there, that, you know, the world is not just made up of what is the scientific
material mathematical world, right? But there it is colored in, it is filled in by our subjectivity
in our experience, right? And a fairly prominent
orthodox person said we sounded like postmodernists. Yeah, because because we
refer to subjectivity, right? Right. That's not anyone the idea that someone
references subjectivity is having value that does not make you a postmodernist.
No. So if those things aren't what postmodernism is, what is it? Okay. Well,
What we call
It's story time kids. No
What we call this would be a sucky story to tell you yes, yes, all right kids today
We're gonna learn about the fact yeah, what if I call post modernism is actually post structuralism. Yeah, you say post-structuralism
Yeah, for family reading time
I'm gonna sit down and read them the illusions of postmodernism by Terry Eagleton. Yeah
So yeah, so if it's actually post-structuralism
This.
then would cause someone to ask the question, okay, what structuralism?
Yes, what structuralism. So once again, it's a bunch of French guys.
Instead of 19th century Germans now, we've got mid-20th century French.
Yes, it's a sort of Easter house.
Yeah, that's it.
So postmodernism doesn't begin as sort of the full blown movement of postmodern deconstruction
at all.
that it becomes after World War II, especially in the early 60s. It starts out as just a series
of criticisms of modernism. So modernism, the sort of de facto view of the world in Europe at the time,
Starting at the end of the 19th century, it sort of peaks with Hegel and the Hegel.
immediately after him like marks. You start getting the reaction from people like
Kierkegaard and Nietzsche. And you start getting these critiques of modernism. And those critiques of modernism,
as they start to take hold, as they start to get purchased, right, these critiques. And the modernist
edifice starts to break apart, well, you need something to replace it.
And so we talk about postmodernism or poststructuralism. We're talking about that thing that kind of
replaces it and kind of will explain here in a minute. Right. But as those critiques begin of
modernism, sort of the last gasp of modernism in trying to sustain itself, modernism kind of tries
to retool itself in light of those critiques that are threatening to tear it down. It tries to
reformulate the administration.
Sort of the way Plotinus tries to reformulate Plitenism as Christianity is really putting it into it.
Right.
So, and structuralism is sort of the last school of thought.
Right. So, one of the primary attacks on maternity is on the idea of objectivity.
And as far as the radio already alluded to, a lot of this plays out in terms of literary
criticism. One of the main places of attack on objectivity is in language. Language is
ability to convey meaning.
Yeah, you know, ultimately, like the post structuralists, the deconstructionists, what
they say is that...
that language cannot actually convey meaning.
You know, we all are talking around each other,
but no one is actually communicating
because like how do you know,
how do you know that the sounds you're making
are received in the same way that you intend them?
Well, it's not just that, right?
Going beyond that, right?
So you have to look at,
so the modernist consensus throughout most of the modern period
is the
way they saw language working, we'll use writing as an example is I have an idea in my
head. Right. Right. I write that idea down. If I write it well, right. So they took it
to account the fact that I could be a lousy writer. Okay. But if I write it well, then
when I give that to you and you read it, you will have the exact same idea in your head.
Yeah, yeah, I want to know.
Yeah, no.
No noise in the channel, it all comes through.
Transferred an idea from my head to your head.
Yeah, and so like what you get.
And what you get with a lot of this kind of post-ructuralist theory is,
like they'll talk a lot about the sign and, you know,
the signifier or the sign and the signified.
Yes. Right? So the word is the signifier or the sign and the signified
is the thing that it refers to.
they'll say, well, it's not the same thing.
There's a, and you know, Derri Dau particularly uses this word.
He takes the French word, difference and replaces the last,
while the second to last E with an A,
Différe Rance, which to me sounds like exactly the same thing.
But anyways, he spells it differently.
And, and which, you know, him doing that is kind of a joke, right?
He's saying that it's, he's, it's a very meta kind of, and very French sort of joke.
But it's a philosophical joke.
And it's essentially saying that the spin...
between these things is so significant that all words, all signs are ultimately arbitrary
and like it's a way of taking nominalism and really pushing it to the very edge of its limits.
And so that real communication is not actually possible. We are all living in a solipsistic
like, box.
Ultimately.
I mean, it's very depressing.
You're kinda going to an extreme here, right?
I-
I know, I know, but you know, I want to start with, I want to start with the parts that are actually true and vital.
I was going to say I'm reliving, I'm reliving some of my 90s trauma.
Yeah, studying at a UWF.
But I'll say, I will say though, I had this one professor and God rest his soul, Tom Hester.
So for anybody who studied under Tom Hester at North Carolina State University back in the day,
amazing man.
He went through all this, explained all this stuff.
And he said, you know what that is that they discovered?
this distance between the sign and the signifier, they discovered sin. Congratulations, you guys.
You discovered sin. I'll leave it with that. Okay. So, yeah, I don't think it's a more basic
level. Right. Have a little PTSD from some of the stuff. Because, of course, that previous
This modern theory is bogus.
Right.
The idea, I just directly convince.
I'm sitting here on the radio.
right now. Yeah. I'm holding a pen in my hand. Now when I said that, you could have a mental
image of my hand holding a pen, right? But what are the odds that the pen you're thinking of looks
like the pen I'm holding? Yeah. And I mean, every day, every day someone reads something that you
or I have written or heard that we've said and misinterpreted it. Right. Well, it's
difference in differently than we intended.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, I mean, and you know, you're pretty decent rider,
especially when you get...
editor on there. Or three. So right, even if I give more descriptors about the pen, if I say,
oh, it's a blue pen, right, the more descriptors I give, the closer it may get. Yeah. But we'll
let ever be precisely the pen. Well, you ever have in your head precisely the pen I'm holding
and looking at. And how would I ever know? Right. Yeah. So that critique, right? So we have this valid
and critique of the way like
So structuralism, here's that, right?
It says, yeah, that's true.
Right?
You know, I can describe a character, I can spend pages, right?
I can be JRR Tolkien and spend, you know, 30 pages describing a forest.
And what 30 pages they will be, yes.
And still, and still, the guy reading it may have a different image of it in his head of the forest.
in his head of the forest.
than I intended. Absolutely. Right. Absolutely. So people have to take this on board. Right.
There's truth to this. Right. You can't just dismiss this. Right.
Um, and you can't just pull a Kant, like Father Andrew just did, and say, well, if that's true,
then all communication is impossible. So I reject it. Right.
Um, because that's, I mean, that's precisely Nietzsche's reputation of Kant. Kant is like, well,
If x, y, and z are true, then logical thought is impossible.
and Nietzsche says, who said logical thought was possible?
Burn it all down.
You're just assuming that.
You're just assuming that logical thought is possible.
Right.
So they say, we're going to take this on board.
And so structuralism then advances the theory that
the language itself, or if it's a body of language,
like a story in and of itself,
contains the meaning within it objectively.
So it has nothing to do with the mind of the author and the mind of the reader.
The meaning is there on the page in the words.
Okay. That structuralism.
Right? So the symbol itself is the thing signified, essentially.
right? So I had an Old Testament professor who was very much a structuralist.
one point in my lifetime of graduate study, right? And he would say when you were handing
in an exigenical paper interpreting a biblical passage, he would say, if you do your job
correctly, you'll also see here why structuralism is a form of modernism. You will be able
to get together a Christian, a Jew, and a Muslim. And point at that old
of it passage and go through the original language with them and say this is what it means
and they'll all agree with you. Yeah. Because that's just what the language means. Right? That's
structuralism and you can see how it's a form of modernism. It's this idea that it's objective,
It's there on the page, it's there in the language.
And I've also had Straussian
Perfect.
and stuff, adds, this can go to crazy places.
Right?
Like the Sycamore tree at the beginning,
Sycamore tree is always represent death, supposedly.
There is a symbol of death always everywhere.
It's hard to do this without some kind of
Jungian idea in the background, right?
Cause why would be writing about a Sycamore tree
and Plato in 4th century BC
Athens writing about a sicklemore tree and the sicklemore tree that's a keyest climbs
to see Jesus all represent death.
But this is a real professor I had.
At the beginning of Plato's laws, there's a sicklemore tree that represents death.
So the whole discussion, we have to frame the whole discussion in the shadow of death
because there's this tree.
suspension.
at the beginning, right? And you can very see how this can go in weird galaxy brain directions,
right? Like the collar, like we were talking about with the collar, of making a lot of false connections.
Right? Making a lot of false connections and too many, too many pins, too many strings on the
the cork board, right?
Going down this road, but it was an attempt
to salvage objectivity.
Yeah, right. It was an attempt to sell a job activity by putting it into the language itself. And so this is why
When you get the full blown post structuralists who we call postmodernists like Derrida
Right, they're attacking language. They have to attack the language itself
Because their opponents were arguing that the language itself sort of contains the meaning
Right. Yeah, that the patterns are objective
Right, and let me say there's some legitimacy to that.
Right? Sure. And this is this is one of the things that drives me nuts and should drive you nuts. You should be suspicious.
Right. Any time any Christian person for example says, well, if you could read this in the Greek.
Yeah. The Greek word means this. Right. Why should you be suspicious of that? Well, this person doesn't know the original language.
Why do they think that word in Greek means that?
means that.
Yeah, because someone told them that or a book, Alexa.
in. Yeah. Somebody wrote that lexicon. Yeah. I mean, it's, if it's
a lexicon of biblical Greek, this is why I use ladel Scott. I use the
general Greek lexicon, not the New Testament Greek lexica, because
ladel and Scott, the ladel and ladel Scott, by the way, is the
father of Alice Little, who Alice in Wonderland was written about.
Do you have the little little, the middle little or the great Scott?
I have the great Scott.
Ooh, I have an old-
middle little, but I also have the great Scott. Wow.
Right. I use them. But even those, right, reflect the views of the people, but they weren't particularly
Christian. So there's fewer theological biases in terms of the New Testament. But
people are coming to add the post-structuralists are right. People who are putting those lexicon
together have biases. Yeah, it's it's it's it's turtles all the way down. They're not totally objective.
Right? There is...
is no Greek word has an objective meaning is equal to an English word. That's not how
language is work. Right. Yep. Right. Translation is an art. You're trying to get at the usage
of that word in a particular context by using a particular English word in that same context,
but there's never a one-to-one kind of correlation.
Right.
Um.
That's about so that's what structuralism is and that's why what we call post modernism is really post structuralism
It's really it takes the form the deconstruction that Daredo is doing for example is a deconstruction of structuralism
It's deconstruction
Yeah, I'm not sure right the the basic problem is yes, you can look at texts you can look at the world you can look at whatever and see
patterns and so forth. Of course.
But there is a selectivity of attention, you know, like the patterns that you see are the patterns that you see.
It's not the only thing that's there. That's like one of my favorite jokes when someone says you're just saying they're doing nothing as I say, well actually on a cellular level, I'm really quite busy.
You know, because there's a massive complex set of patterns that are happening in the human body that are totally invisible.
invisible and maybe you're more important than anything else.
I'm doing at the moment.
You know, for example, you rest on your laurels.
Yeah.
And so really what we're talking about, what we're talking about post modernism
is the rejection of certain elements of modernity.
Right.
The rejection of positivism, meaning the idea, so positivism is essentially the
the modern idea that we can...
know things for certain using scientific methodology.
And eventually by correctly applying scientific methodology,
we can know everything.
Oh yeah, I mean, I think that that's the basic assumption
that a lot of people have without usually saying it.
Yes, yes.
And if you read, go and read the introduction,
the preface, the prologomina,
to Hodges systematic theology.
Is it?
time.
Presbyterian scholar at Old Princeton
in the 19th century. But despite being conservative as we would use it religiously in terms of
his beliefs, right? And not on the modernist side, more on the fundamentalist side,
for what would come later, he has a died in the wool modernist. Because he says that
is that it is probably a governor that the text of scripture is data.
Wow.
But if we properly analyze and arrange the data that theology is a science and the results
of correctly doing biblical theology are just as certain as the results of physics or
the other natural sciences.
So that's positivism.
That's in a religious, in a Christian religious context, that's positivism.
This sort of great confidence.
So
So post-modernism attacks that.
Says, that's nonsense.
Right.
You can know some things with relative degrees of certainty.
But you can't know anything with that degree of certainty.
And you definitely can't know everything.
Yeah.
With any degree of certainty at all.
Right.
Post-modernism attacks the idea of objectivity.
I
the idea that that anyone is ever objective as we've said on the show quoting Thomas Nagel
There is no view from nowhere
Okay, those two criticisms by the way I think are pretty much entirely valid
Yeah
Right may have heard me way back in the log-a-go time when one of the conversations I had with Pazzo
I said well one of the good things about postmodernism is it helped destroy modernism right so
So these are these critiques
aren't invalid, right? Now they're going to go a little further though, right? So post-modernism is
going to say there are no universals. Yeah. Universals don't exist. There are only particulars.
This is this is why a lot of people use post-modernism that word as a kind of synonym for relativism.
right. Yeah. All generalizations are false.
which is a hysterical statement. Right. But I've even heard someone say all generalizations
are false, including that one. Yeah. Which is amazing. So and then based on that, the existence of truth
as such. Right. Meaning some kind of objectives, truth, some kind of truth that could be accessed
by everyone.
But you notice, it's just a series of rejections. It's just a series of critiques. It doesn't actually
replace modernism with anything. Yeah, it's just burning it down. And that's why it's referred
to as postmodernism or post structuralism. It doesn't have any actual positive name for itself,
because it isn't anything. Yeah. And doesn't pretend to be anything really. Yeah. It's just a
deconstruction of modernism and thus post-modernism.
And so, you know, we need to double deeper, because the origins, the origins of postmodernism,
as I mentioned earlier, are really in the earliest reactions against modernism.
That's where the first little pieces.
It's just at that point arguments against modernism.
Because modernism became ascendant and went around.
And its origins ultimately come out of politics.
Now people are going to get scared, but we're talking about 18th and 19th century European
politics.
If it applies at all to 2024 politics, let the reader do that on his own.
Yeah.
Um, right, so...
And it happens in a move to and a transformation of the political right.
Now, as I say that, if you don't live in the United States, you have a general idea of what I mean.
If you live in the United States, you don't know what I mean by that, right?
because American politics is weird and goofy and basically
profitable.
just two teams, people root for their team.
Right.
Yes, so, so, so traditional.
We'll write this left in terms of social issues.
Yeah, right.
You stand on various social issues,
historically and even now, like I would say probably in Europe,
to be right wing is to be kind of more monarchist, more, you know,
we're talking about the period where the right wing were monarchists
and supported the landage.
in the nobility and the left wing were revolutionaries who wanted to overthrow
hereditary monarchies and establish Guzhuwa democracy. Yeah, like that's the right the left
we're talking about. Old European conservatism was about like habits and traditions,
you know, like conserving things. Like we've always done it that way and and we should continue
to do it that way because we respect the wisdom of the centuries, the collection of the the
the things that our people
kind of worked out over time as the way we do things.
Yeah.
You know, and here's how foreign this is to the current American way of thinking.
Uh, I don't know.
Almost no Americans today would identify the founding fathers of the United States as
radical leftists, even though they all were in their time.
Oh, yeah.
But radical in a sense, they picked up guns and shot at British soldiers.
Right.
By these.
Yeah.
traditional
considerations. Yeah. Right. Yeah. So this is very different than the way we use right
left in America today. Okay. So don't assume there's a one-to-one correlation. Right.
So there is of course as modernism begins, there is of course this struggle. And this struggle
is also related to the rise of capitalism, where you have the rise of bourgeois society,
you have people who are not hereditary nobility.
who become wealthy, because you move from feudalism to capitalism.
Right? And so these people start to become wealthy.
They have financial and monetary power, but they don't have social and political power,
because that's all held by the nobility. Right?
And so the tenants of modernism that we were talking about,
start to tear at this. They say, well, look,
there's no difference between me and the king.
Right. In fact, the king was just born to the previous king. I've worked my whole life
at a mass this fortune. Yeah. Right. And the policies the king makes, they affect me.
He's taxing me on my wealth. He's making laws that make it harder for me to do business
and trade. Right. I should be the one making those decisions that affect me off with his
right and it's
When this goes there, when the French Revolution in particular, a little bit with the American
Revolution, but then especially the French Revolution, because of course, the American
revolutionaries couldn't get it King George if they wanted to, right?
Yeah.
Guys like Thomas Payne, who got thrown out of Britain for being a radical leftist, were
the kind of guys who would have killed the king if they got the chance, but they didn't.
But in France they do, and the reign of terror starts.
The reign of terror starts in the name of enlightenment, reason, right?
Liberté, egalité, fraterité, all of these modernist values, right?
This is an eruption of modernism.
And so when you look at the reaction, when you look at Burke in particular, the founding
father of traditional conservative philosophy, you look at Emman Burke's response to the
French Revolution.
And what is he saying? What is his...
argument against the French Revolutionaries, right, against the Jacobins. His argument is,
one of his central arguments is that they claim to know universal truth. They claim to have access
to universal reason. And Burke says those things don't exist. There are only particular people,
in particular places, in particular times, in particular cultures, particular traditions.
And that those are the things that have value.
Not these pretended universal rights, universal egalitarianism, none of this.
And you can see there the seeds in Burke's conservatism of what will become the postmodern
critique of modernity.
Yeah.
Right?
You can see the seeds, seeds there and seed for it.
And so.
Post-modernism is actually a way of thinking that far more often conservative people fall into than the opposite.
People who are actual liberals tend to end up becoming modernists.
Yeah, because there's a big program to make everything awesome.
And people who are conservative bent, the dangers that they slip into kind of a post-modern...
view in their attack on on the modernists, right? Yeah, I remember I remember, um, I'm see,
this is again, this is bringing up all of my, my, uh, my 90s, my 90s literary theory triggers.
But I remember, um, Dr. Hester, who I mentioned earlier, uh, someone asked it with Uncle Fester.
Yeah, no, not to be confused at all. Um, yeah, someone asked him like, so, you know,
because he was describing structural...
and post-structuralism, all this sort of stuff.
And someone asked him, like, well, what in this view
does anything mean then?
How do you understand life?
And he says, look, if you really boil this down to this,
and this is, he's talking about this question of particulars.
So if you really boil it down, life is just one damned thing
after another.
That's what he said.
I was like, oh man.
Why could you do that?
I'm on the air.
Yeah, I know.
Well, you know, we could talk about damnation.
that.
It's in Hellfire and.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But yeah, I mean, that's right.
Like, it's like, when you really embrace
this kind of post-ructuralist stuff,
then there isn't any way to interpret or understand
there's no story at all, right?
I mean, this is one of, this is,
right, people like to talk about things.
That's not how they see things working.
Yeah, the meaning crisis,
because, you know, what story is there?
Meaning is it out there to be found,
Which is a good segue.
Right, right? Where does it come from that?
Right, I'll tell you where it comes from
Where does it my friends and I use well
Sometimes I would like to have Nietzsche as a friend. I would never like to have Michelle Foucault as a friend
Yeah, no, yeah like Foucault and Lacan
Super creepy. Yeah, like there's not enough. There's not really enough purel for me to hang around with Michelle Foucault
never look up their lives unless you have a
strong stomach people. But I don't know, Nietzsche seems fun at parties. Yeah, cool mustache.
Right. So Nietzsche and Fuku don't live at the same time. Right. So Nietzsche is at the end of the 19th
century. And we get a couple of things right from Nietzsche and Fuku's and Nietzsche. So Fuku
is deliberately building on Nietzsche. But the couple of pieces you get from
that affect this kind of postmodernism.
Number one, on the critique level,
Nietzsche ultimately argues for a kind of perspective.
Ism. Right?
There is no truth, there's always perspectives on truth,
there's no reality, there's always perspectives on reality.
Yeah.
So when I describe the pen,
I'm just describing how the pen appears to me.
I have no way of even knowing that if you were here
in the room with me looking at the same pen
that it would look the same to you as it does to me.
Yeah, I can-
inside your head. Right. And so, right, he goes now that way. So this idea that there aren't facts,
there are just perspectives. Right. There's no truth out there. There's just perspectives, ideas,
viewpoints, interests, desires. Right. That's what there exists. But there are no facts. There's no
no shared reality even. And Nietzsche gives the great man theory of history.
or at least a classical example of it. I would say Plutarch has a great man theory of history, but
the great man theory of history being that there are these certain watershed points in history where
a great man comes along and that great man redefines human life and civilization basically by the
force of his will and charisma. Right? So you don't have stories out there that have any meaning or
or help.
you discover meaning in the world, but you have a great man who comes and tells you a story,
and the story he tells you gives you meaning or reframes what the world means and even is.
Right. And so he identifies, for example, Jesus of Nazareth as one of these people.
He doesn't like the way Christianity transformed the world, but it did. Right. He acknowledges that it
did. Right, he hates...
how it transported the world, but he acknowledged it and it transformed the world.
And his whole thing with the uberman, the overman who's coming is he's talking about the next
there's going to be a next great man who comes and is going to redefine all this now because he was
convinced that the sort of Christian era in Europe was over and by all signs 125 years later
it is still kind of looking like that.
sadly, but that someone was going to come and was going to then, you know, reevaluate all
values.
Was going to come and transform everything.
And of course, this invited somebody like Adolf Hitler to come and present himself and
say, Oh yeah, I'm that guy.
Right?
Follow me, right?
Yeah.
Even though Nietzsche would have hated him.
like virulently, uh, but he presents that view.
Right. And this is very much drawing on these figures like Alexander the Great Napoleon. Right.
So the way Michelle Foucault kind of develops that is that Foucault says, well, there are people who are in power
regardless of how they've come to have it. They have it. And
they can use that power. They can use what he calls force. And force for him is not always like physical force or violence.
It could be force of will, force of persuasion, force of personality, right? All those things are in the force.
But they come and they define things. So he takes sort of Nietzsche's great man,
Aduruch, and says, well, it's a little more diffuse than that.
Right? So like the king of a country, or even the president or prime minister of a country,
has to some degree the ability to do that within their own country.
And so they will redefine language.
They will invent new language.
They will do that.
And by doing that, they will reframe the way
a given group of people under their power,
perceive the world.
Right?
They will change the world that those people live in,
sort of buy this assertion of force.
Right?
And this is, we-
We talked once before we were talking about madness the episode where we talked about madness which I think was one of our Halloween episodes maybe
Yeah, yeah
We we talked about some of Foucault's early work where on on madness where he visited St. Asylums and he did a lot of
Actually work on this and he talked about how the idea of madness had changed historically to mean different things
Right that in the ancient world madness meant somebody was touched by the gods. It was special and had some kind of
secret wisdom, right? And then later on in the medieval period, he says, you know,
shows how madness became this category of, uh, opposes the king, right? Uh, is it willing
to conform to society's rules? Right? This woman isn't willing to live the way our society says
she should live. So she's mad. She's crazy. Put her in asylum. Um, and then it evolved again to,
to what we now talk about mental illness, where we've metacolized.
the idea of madness. We talk about it in a very different way now. Right? And so from Foucault's perspective,
right, there's no reality that's changed. Right? But the way in which we view this,
as completely and radically been redefined multiple times in human history. Right? And so this is just
something that happens through sort of the force of persuasion, these other things.
He, he, he.
defines as horse. So as we mentioned, there is this correct critique of modernism
contained in there about objectivity not being real. That scientific or material reality
is does not is not the same thing as reality is such. There are things that are real that
aren't scientifically measurable, right, or don't subsist in material, but they're still
real. And it is correct that...
Universal's are abstractions, whereas particulars really exist.
Okay, this is a sorry Plato and anyone out there who's Plato brained, right?
Chair does not exist.
They're just a whole lot of chairs.
Right, and we abstract from all those particular chairs to say, well, this is what makes a chair a chair because this is what they all have in common.
Right.
Um.
But postmodernism then because all it has is that critique, is it follows that critique through to the opposite extreme.
So whereas modernism will only acknowledge that what is quote unquote, quote unquote objective, that what is scientifically measurable that is mathematically quantifiable. That's all that's real.
Postmodernism will say no, only subjectivity is real.
All of those things are language games that people are playing.
They don't necessarily connect to reality in any way.
Everyone just lives in their own subjectivity all the time.
There is no reality.
There's no factual reality that anyone has access to.
Like sure there's material reality out there probably, right?
But you don't have any access to it.
All you have access to is your perspective, your perceptions of it.
And then ultimately...
There's this denial that things have natures, that things are anything.
Right?
The object, the particular object I was talking about is not really a chair.
I call it a chair because I've decided it's a chair and I'm going to sit on it.
But there is nothing about it in and of itself that makes it a chair.
And that then gets applied to humans.
There is no...
human nature. That is a any kind of trans-historical, transnational, universal reality, which obviously
causes a lot of problems for a view of humanity. So it's this opposite extreme.
right so what does what do manifestations
of postmodern Christianity look like. We talked about modern Christianity. What is postmodern Christianity look like?
Well, something happened in the early 80s. And that's evangelicalism which had been a form of Protestantism,
It had been the conservative form of Protestantism became a political movement.
Yeah, yeah, right. I mean, that's not all it is right. No, but, but, but it really
very self-consciously there was a sense of like, we need to take back our country, you know,
and give a voting block. Take this country for God, you know, and that means politics.
Very clearly, right. A political movement. Right. And, and by that, right, Foucault's force,
We need to...
grasp the reins of power and use them to
Restructure the country the way we want it to be
the way we think it should be the way we believe it should be right yeah
And
You see the language
Right, you see the language
Of values we've talked about this before on the show, but the language of values showing up within that political the political part of that movement
Right.
not so much of the religious part, but in the political part of the movement, we start using the word values.
And we've talked before on the show that comes from Schailer's value theory. The idea being there's a neutral moral landscape out there.
Nothing is really good or bad, but there are things that we value.
We as a particular culture value.
I mean, that's practical. You are about to quote Hamlet literally.
over nothing is good or bad but thinking makes it so yeah
So yeah, it's valuing right so yes we in our culture we in our family we hear we in the our community we value honesty
Yeah, right but honesty is not better than lying
Objectively because there's no objective right yeah, it's just this is what we value and so you get that language of values
They're talking about family values right values
Yeah, and a lot of people who talk about those things that's they wouldn't say that
honesty in lying or objectively the same, but we we happen to think that honest we want honesty,
but the problem is that language of values basically is assuming that right that's the
position under that language. This is what valuable to us right and you can see the difference in
approach. So a modern approach to this would be here I have all of these studies done by social
scientists at universities showing that
intact families benefit society in ways xyz right we're gonna we're gonna put together scientific evidence
That's the model to support the point that this is what we should do that's the modernist approach right yeah, yeah
the postmodern
Approach is we believe in family values
This is what we need to do
And it doesn't matter what studies show get out of here with your studies
We're suspicious of the studies. Yeah. Yeah. Because you're a bunch of modernists, which means you're
probably a bunch of liberals, right? Like that's so get out of here with that, right? That's the
difference, right? And approach that postmodernism asserts just asserts beliefs and values. And when
someone pushes back on that assertion, rather than making some kind of argument or trying to prove
prove that their point is true.
by giving some kind of facts, right? The postmodern approach just asserts with more force.
Asserts more forcefully. Yeah, which I mean, that's in a lot of ways that sort of
shouting everything down is kind of where we are with a lot of stuff now. Right. You know,
just scream it out.
Yeah.
Right.
Um, another example of where we see post-war and Christianity.
Have you noticed all the particular study Bibles?
Yeah.
There's so many study Bibles.
The Med Study Bible, the Women's Study Bible, the Children's Study Bible, the Patriot Bible,
the Patriot Study Bible with the big American flag on the cover.
I know that.
On and on.
And not just that, we gotta be fair, right?
Lutheran study Bible, Reformed study Bible, Orthodox study Bible.
Yeah.
Seattle care Bobby.
I'll just say this stuff on the.
A lot.
Hey.
The following that represent the opinions of just right.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Put the disclaimer back on.
Where's that disclaimer?
Right.
Where this isn't present where where the way this is being presented
is here is a fill in the blank.
view or interpretation or reading of the scriptures. Yeah. A version. Yeah. Not. Here's what this means.
Right. But here's what this means from this perspective. Right. That is a post-modern approach.
And also a good way to make a lot of money.
for Bible publishing houses that print all these dozens of different study
cycles. Yeah. Just go to Amazon and type in study Bible and it's just just
keep scrolling just scroll. Yeah. And then when when you go to a Bible study
the CSB apologetic study Bible. Yeah. The CSB everyday study Bible. Sorry, it just goes on
I don't know.
You do these-
Bible studies in churches and Christian groups that are basically reader-response Bible studies.
Meaning, they don't ask the question, what does this mean?
They say, what does this mean to me?
What does it mean to me?
Right.
Here's how this affects my life.
Meaning, here's how this interacts with my own subjectivity.
Right.
Not what does this mean.
What's the danger of that?
Well whatever you're reading is, is rarely going to challenge your subject.
activity. Right. Very rarely do you go to those reader response style Bible studies and
somebody says, wow, I read this and I realized I was totally wrong about XYZ. Yeah. Right.
And if you're only using a study Bible that you already agree with, that will never happen.
Right.
Um, um,
um,
You get worship that's aimed at not doing something, right?
Where our worship, our ritual is doing something, is accomplishing something, but aimed at producing
a kind of religious experience.
Yeah, right.
We're going to come together and try to have this experience.
And if it doesn't happen enough times in a row, we go somewhere else chasing that experience
again.
Right, but it's this subjective experience with
looking for not any kind of objective. Right. It's not I'm going to go and receive the
Eucharist, which I know is going to grant me healing of body and soul, the forgiveness
of sins, draw me closer to correct. No, that kind of it's I'm going to go and we're going
to have a great time of worship. I'm going to leave feeling really inspired.
Yeah. I mean, and this is the basis for a lot of people asking the question like, well,
What it was it mean for me to participate?
You know it.
Yeah, because it's people looking to get something out of it,
quote unquote, you know.
And it leads to, in terms of way of life and ethics,
you get just this kind of broad tolerance
that's based on there being any kind of objective standard,
right, because we can't actually know anything for sure,
right?
So, right, well, what does that mean?
Right? What does that mean?
For example, if you've got a modernist, if you've got a modernist who's in favor of
receiving same-sex married people into their church body, right?
The modernist will go and give you super convoluted ways of reading all of the biblical passages
that seem to condemn homosexuality but arguing they
don't really. Right? They'll give you this huge like I see if you look at if you
if you do a word study of this Hebrew word in this it refers to temple
prostitutes and not not not not you get all that from a modernist. Right?
You talk to a postmodernist who believes in the same thing. The postmodernist
will just say to you something like, well God loves everyone.
Love is love.
We're you to judge, right? It's a very different
Right approach
Right because the modernists still thinks there's objective reality out there that they have to account for and work around
Right, whereas the postmodernist doesn't
um
And in terms of the self we talked about how
Now for the modernist yourself, your soul is something.
fixed you go and you try and find it you go try and figure out who you are right whereas
in a postmodern approach the self is completely protean meaning it's it's everybody knows
who proteases don't they?
either no Greek method or you know X-Men comics go on you got to know one or two at least
anyway.
I can't be playing no super.
Protein means ever shifting and changing.
Yes.
See God is a see God you guys, right? So everything is constantly fluid kind of a lesser see God not not beside kind of everything is constantly fluid. It's not who am I to am I now?
Yeah, who am I today? Who am I going to be in this situation? It's it's it's you know to use two phrases that we hear a lot. I was born this way versus the modernist approach. That's the modernist one versus I identify as.
Yes, that's the Prodian.
So the earlier modernist view was, you know,
for your lows, the person was born that way.
That's who they are, right?
You can't change that.
Right?
Whereas the post-bottled approach is, this is what I identify as.
This is how I'm choosing to express myself today.
It might be different tomorrow.
Right?
So different.
Right.
So what?
you know, in terms of our assessment, in terms of our criteria, what could we say about post-modern
Christianity? Is it false Christianity or is it something else? And I'm going to go ahead and say
it's something else. Why? Well, because there's, for example, there are no authority structures.
Yes, there's not even a continuity of authority structures, you know, an alteration of authority
structures, it just not. There aren't any. It's, it's, it's, it's really just cults of personality
in a lot of ways. I mean, that's the worst version.
of it, but the best version is still like, it's based on charisma and, and ability and
whatever. There's no like apostolic succession or any version.
There's not even ordination really.
Yeah, not really.
Yeah. It's like Mussolini or Kennedy.
It's a cult of personality.
But yeah, it's just for so charisma, right?
If, if I want to be a leader within postmodern Christianity, what do I need to do?
I need to create a YouTube account.
Yeah, talented. Hopefully good look. Maybe. Maybe or say things that make people. Yeah, right.
That's it. Right. And if I get enough views, I am now a leader. I am now a Christian leader.
I am now a Christian teacher. No one's laid hands on me. Yeah. No one's ordained me. No one sent me
aside to this ministry? No one's done anything. I just made a YouTube account. Who's the bishop that
commissioners who care and as soon as people turn on me because I say the right thing wrong thing
I'm done. Yeah, yeah, this kind of authority is taken down by cancel culture. Right. But it actually
means there's no real authority. Yeah, if I can't say anything to my audience that they don't want
to hear, I don't have any authority over them. That's right, because authority is about being able to
correct people. Yeah. So we say there's no authority structures. Not only are there no structures,
There's also no authority.
There's not either of them.
It's just a force of charisma and force.
It is for exactly what Foucault called force.
They have no functioning scriptures.
Okay. What do you mean by that?
Because I mean by that.
Yeah, because obviously they're all reading the Bible.
So the president, the now former president.
Now I think deceased, actually, former president of a reformed seminary in the United States
that was not even regarded as all that liberal at the time he was president.
Said to me, the hardest thing he had had to deal with in his decades of ministry
were people who said the Bible says this and that.
And this man said because the Bible doesn't say...
say anything. You interpret the Bible as saying that. Yeah. So in what sense are the scriptures?
Anything. Right. It's really the case. Yeah. Because they can be anything. And this is why you get this vast swath of identity politics readings of Scripture.
If you've had the misfortune, the American Academy of Religion is even worse than SBL.
on this, but African-American readings of scriptures, feminist readings of scripture,
queer readings of scripture.
Right.
And that's these papers, a queer reading of Ezekiel chapter three, right?
Oh yeah.
Right.
And all these things.
Now, I'm in favor of everyone reading the scriptures.
Yes.
Women, African-Americans, right?
Even gay people should read the scriptures.
Right.
you
when it's approached in this Perspectival Postmodern Way of just, well, here's what it says to me
based on my group identity. Right? Based on my individual identity. This is what this says to me as a
fill in the blank. Right? You're ready to trouble when someone starts any sentence with as a blank.
right? But as a right, this is what says to be as a data.
that it out, that's implying that the text by itself doesn't say anything. The meaning
only comes out of the subjectivity of the reader, right, which is a postmodern approach, right,
which means like that seminary president said to me, the Bible doesn't say anything. Well,
if the Bible doesn't say anything, you don't have scriptures. Yeah. Right. Not the function
with
any kind of authority. Yeah, I mean, how could you, how could, you know, the, the father's
wrote the creed ever say according to the scriptures, quoting the scriptures, by the way, when
they said that. But in what does that even mean? If it's really just, if it's really just
individually subjective. Right. Yeah. Yeah. There's, and in terms of material reality, of course
the postmodern, there's no objective material reality out there.
Bad or good? Right there is no such thing right
And so
This post water forms of Christianity are completely artificial because each person is constructing it
Within and based on their own subjectivity
Right just go on YouTube and watch random evangelical videos
Right?
I was just, I did that today.
I watched one where a guy was talking about
because of my dissertation, kind of a pet hobby thing.
This guy was talking about why he,
even though he was raised to believe
in Pedal Substitutionary Atonement,
this young guy no longer believes in it.
There's no why he believes in it.
And it's just a list of things he found troubling about it.
Wow.
He gives a list of things he found troubling about it.
And then he says, and I did some research, I found out there were other ways of looking at it.
Wow. And this particular way of looking at it really appealed to me.
Wow. So it comes down to, I didn't like it. And I like this. So there was no, what is true?
Yeah. Right. What did Christ do for me when he died on the cross and rose again?
Yeah. What did he do for me? The incarnation. That's not the question that's asked.
Yeah, you know, I mean it's one of the ways of looking
got it in which one appeals to me?
I left evangelicalism about 30 years ago.
And it really, I mean, it is not evangelicalism I grew up with.
It's just not.
It's really gone way down this road.
And so what you have are these foreign elements bearing
Christian-ish terminology.
And it's something else.
So if modernism gets to deform,
Christianity produces what we might call liberal Protestantism or just liberal Christianity in general
because there are liberals in the Roman Catholic Church, there are liberals in the Orthodox
Church even. Not a lot, but they're noisy. Then post-modernism produces a lot of contemporary
even jalicorism. Yep. And it's a little more insidious.
Because you can very much have postmodern conservatism.
Yeah, yeah, like you can identify a liberal by their conclusions
Right, whereas postmodernism is purely an issue of method
Not of conclusions
You could be a postmodernist and arrive at any set of conclusions. You could be a postmodern trad
You can say this traditional way of life is what appeals
to me, so I'm going to do it. Yeah, I mean, I find it useful in certain ways.
To me, the classic postmodern trad is the kind of person. And frankly, it's usually a guy
that, you know, like for him, like liturgics is kind of a boutique shop of cool stuff.
Yeah. There are tradwives who approach it in a very postmodern way. There are women
which is this is the lifestyle I want to live.
Yeah.
Yeah, you know
So that's you know
So these these are currents that are at work
You know, so we're not just saying like oh all you evangelicals are postmodernists and all you mainline
Protestants are all modernists
We're saying
There's a swath
Right at least as we look at American Christianity. There's a swath of
of liberal Protestantism and liberal Roman Catholicism.
and liberals within the Orthodox Church, right? They have less power to do things in the Orthodox Church.
They're still there. That's why they're so noisy. They're always complaining.
Right? And there are plenty of people who approach things in a postmodern way, right?
Yeah.
In outside of evangelicalism, right? You don't find a lot of postmodernists actually in
in mainline liberalism because they're all dedicated modernists. That's sort of their whole thing.
But it definitely is where evangelicals
tend to slide and where it has slid
over the past several decades.
We are also going to be self-critical.
Yep, here, not as we begin, but in the third half.
But so now the third half we're going to talk about,
okay, so now that this bleak picture has been painted,
what do we do?
So what?
So, all right, well, you've wasted another perfectly good hour of your life on the
Lord of Spirits podcast, so we're going to take our second and final break and we'll be right back.
We're back now.
The existence of fools for Christ in the Orthodox tradition mystifies many people, even some
within the Orthodox Church itself.
People often wonder what purpose these sometimes comical and often times tragically misunderstood
saints serve in the life of the Church, especially given their unconventional and seemingly
bizarre behaviors.
holy fools by us.
When Creighton, we begin to gain a better understanding of these saints' curious manner of serving
Christ, as we learn about the extraordinary lives of 20 of the most well-known fools for Christ
in a series of brief hagiographies.
Available now at store.enginefaith.com
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father-Andre Stephen-Damek, and Father Stephen
de Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back.
It's the third half of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
We're back now.
Are we back now?
Yeah, I think so.
Okay.
And we're back.
Before we roll onto the third half,
we actually have...
a caller from the great white north who has been waiting very patiently since
sometime near the beginning of the second half.
Oh, wow.
So I know.
I know.
So Roger, this is your moment.
How are things in Kanaka's stand?
Hi, Father.
Thank you for taking my call.
Yeah.
What's up?
As a joke, even, well, I have a question, but as a joke, even the,
the naturalists found a way to just apply, yeah.
by the Bible, their way of life and Christianity.
But my question is, last time I had the question
about if Christ would have came
even though Adam would not have seen,
and you gave me a perfect answer.
But now I have a small question to that,
is in the testimony, when they say
that Christ had to come and die,
Are they saying that he has...
to come or they're just saying Christ died for our sins. Like are they saying that he
had to come or is just describing what happened for four, seven, like four? I don't know if
it makes sense or not. So you're asking if it was a matter of necessity? Is that what
you're saying? Yeah, within the premise of if Christ would have came, that Christ would
I don't even know I don't know how to say it.
because if they would have said had, then I'm trying to fit it that out. But if they just said
he just died and they're just describing what happened. It's like as if we kill them because of our
sin and stuff. But yeah, I mean, Christ's death, I mean, obviously we're in the realm of speculation
Because we all we have is reality
we have, right? But in our world sin did happen and death is introduced into the world. I would
speculate, and I don't know if any of the fathers have said this or what you would say to this
father, Stephen, but that if there had not been a fall that Christ still would have been incarnate,
but that the crucifixion would not have been part of it, because there would be no need to conquer
death because death would not
be in humanity. But again, that's in the world of speculation, right? I don't know. Father,
what do you think? Yeah, I mean, that's basically right, right? I mean,
Jesus wouldn't have died because nobody would have died. Yeah. Yeah. That, that, that situation,
like that hypothetical, right? Yeah. Situation, right? So yeah. So they use the, they actually use
the verb pad.
like an necessity pretty much. Not only he who's there. I know. Yeah, I mean, are you
referencing a specific scripture, a particular verse? Yeah, like one coin since 15.
Yeah. So that's the way this is the fancy theological term for this is,
because this gets into atonement stuff, is a consequent necessity.
meaning given the way the world actually was, right, or is, right, this happening was necessary.
This is what was going to happen because the world is the way it is, right, but it's
consequent necessity because if the world were different than it would not have been.
Right.
Flip.
Yeah.
R
All right, Roger. I hope that answers your question.
Thank you so much.
Thanks for calling.
Thank you.
All right.
We do have another caller lined up who just called in.
So greetings next caller.
Who are we talking to?
Hey, this is Harrison.
Is that me?
Yes, it's you, Harrison.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits by test.
Yeah, thank you, Father.
So thanks for taking my call.
I actually called him fairly late to the episode,
that what I've caught so far.
I've sparked a question that's been on my mind quite a bit for a long time, which is
you know with this discussion of tradition, modernism, postmodernism, evidence,
you know the text sentiment, the feelings of what feels right, what am I being led to?
So for me as somebody coming from a Protestant background, I think I've had some exposure to
you more of the mainline things growing up loose in and then
just a complete evaluation that Turks came back to a more sort of evangelicaly for square
kind of non-denominational ish that might upset some people that was appealing I had.
Since then I've been very drawn the last few years to orthodoxy, more have learned about
it and I could explain more about why that is if that was helpful for anybody listening.
It's been a difficult question for me.
I mean, there are things I really like about this.
I'm like you said, there are people who,
I think I have this temptation to do it
because it's cool, because I like the way it feels.
And I just, a couple weeks ago, went to the best for the first time
and really had a very moving experience that I told the priest after it.
It really feels like I stepped back in time
and he said, oh, I think he stepped out of time.
I got it.
Yeah, you got me.
But it was it really was a different kind of
of feeling but I think I have trouble whenever I start thinking about this.
Like do I actually want to commit to this, and obviously it's a long process, but how do
I know what the right church is?
You know there are churches that have can explain the history and epistolic succession and
all of that.
But when it comes down to it, what do I really have besides the field?
of is this where God wants me?
Yeah, and you know, especially within the context of what we just
been discussing. And I mean, a lot of people have pointed this
out at various times. The act of making a decision to become an
Orthodox Christian as opposed to all the other options in front
of you is a very modern act. Right? Right. Um.
And I mean, here's the thing, in our cultural context,
it's inescapable.
Right? Like, what else can you do?
You know, most people did not grow up
within a context where there are a bunch of religious options.
I mean, certainly, and not even in this way,
like in the first century when the apostles were first
preaching the gospel, they weren't a multi religious context
But not in the sense of like I'm going to pick which religion I like or I want or I think is the right one
It was rather there's all these gods being worshiped and someone could worship
multiple ones in fact most people did
You know, they wouldn't say well. I prefer this one. You know
So in some ways in a lot of ways we're in a historically unprecedented period where people make decisions to join a church
And I don't see a way out of that in America in 2024.
I don't.
I don't think it's right for me, especially as an Orthodox priest
to say, you should just simply stay in whatever you were born
in period no matter what.
Because that's not right either.
So, I mean, one of the things that I discovered
because I...
At least for me becoming an orthodox Christian,
you know, as I've mentioned a couple of times
in this episode, I was raised even dullical,
although more and more I have to say
not like those events, you know, it was different.
It was simply different.
I mean, I was born, father Steven and I were both born
in the same year in the mid 1970s.
So like, but we weren't raised with the same tradition.
He was raised, Dutch reformed.
I was raised kind of Baptistish, you know,
And it was different for sure in the 80s and early 90s than it is now.
But nonetheless, I made a decision to leave that and to become an Orthodox Christian.
That is a modern act.
It's just the way that it is.
And for me, a lot of what I went through at the time was, okay, well, let me try to, as
as much as I can, kind of turn the clock back on.
Christianity and go to the beginning and see which groups veered off when, you know, and
is there any that stayed that did not veer off that remained consistent and continuous, you
know. And that was the way that I now almost 30 years ago made that decision, at least
mentally, intellectually. The thing that really propelled me in terms of wanting to truly...
stay was the power of experiencing Orthodox Christian worship. But ultimately what I would
say to anybody is, and how do I know where to be, is not an answer that I can give that
is going to satisfy an intellectual set of categories. But rather it is, if you have met
Christ and you are willing to turn yourself over to Christ in this particular place, and
is clear to you in this place.
think in good conscience that's where a person should be. That doesn't mean that I agree
that all are equal or the all are right or whatever. I believe that Orthodox Christianity is
the place for that. But if someone is truly seeking God humbly, I can't fault wherever it
is that he happens to be, even if it's not where I think he should be yet. And here's
why because I
I know a people have looked at, like let's just say, for instance, a lot of people that
comes down to a question between Orthodox Christianity and Roman Catholicism, right?
Because they're like, well, these are the two earliest possibilities.
And then some might add on the, what are called the Oriental Orthodox Churches.
Like, okay, I've got these three options in front of me.
Which one is right?
They all have apostolic origins.
I've known a people who looked at all the same evidence.
It really read it all.
Really...
struggle through it all and made different decisions in the end.
And I can't say I know exactly why that is the case.
It would be tempting to say, well, this person's just too stupid to understand the differences.
Or, or, or I mean, no, this is right or two still are too uninformed.
Right?
Like, no, I don't think you really read all the books, you know, or, or that they have an ulterior motive.
Well, you chose this one because, you know, right?
I don't see...
I think that those three things can explain,
and it maybe does explain some,
a lot of choices people make,
but if we're gonna assume good faith,
then we can't assume any of those three things.
Those are things for people to ask themselves,
you know, am I doing this in good faith?
Did I really, you know, whatever?
I will tell you,
I really recently learned of a very distant relative of mine,
like a third cousin in another country,
who I actually just relative
recently met for the first time. And she told me that she had decided to become orthodox,
which shocked me. I was shocked, but it's just bad. I thought, why did I talk to you about
any of this? There's no way I was actually a factor in any way. And I was like, well, why?
And it turned out that she had been stopping at an orthodox church for years to go in light of
a candle and pray and just loved it in there. And I thought to myself, you know...
I cannot fault that even a little bit.
I can't.
Even though that is not a big intellectual journey.
Right?
That is not.
It's not.
So that's what I would say all about that.
I don't know that that's like a satisfactory answer, but I'm going to hand the baton over
to Father Steve and see what he said.
I will say I'm inclined to think that is probably a good answer because it is so on
satisfactory.
seems pretty consistent in my experience.
I think that's mostly what you in particular about swath.
Yeah.
What do you say, father?
I disagree with the vast swath of that.
I think you're wrong.
So let's talk about how you decide the girl you should marry.
And as father Andrew points out, right?
You could say, well, that's a modern question
because for most of human history,
you didn't get.
to pick right?
That was a parents' pick.
So the very idea that you get to pick is, but that's a product of living in the modern
world, right?
It's not modernism to pick.
Yeah.
Right?
The woman you married, that's just the reality of now you're in the modern world, you have
to pick, right?
That's where we are.
I guess you could go to a Yanta or something, but, um, so, so that's where we are.
Okay.
Here are some bad ways to pick the girl you're gonna marry.
Here's way number one.
This is modernism.
You say, this is the girl I should marry because she's got this quality and that quality
and she doesn't have a lot of debt and she has the money and she's from this family and
that'll help me with my career and this and that and she wants to live where I want to
live and, right?
Sort of factual investigation, doing math, right?
This looks like a good ratchet on paper.
So I.
I am going to marry her.
Right?
It's a horrible way to decide who to marry.
Okay?
The other side, this is, and this is like postmodernism.
I am just really into and quasi obsessed with this girl
so I'm going to marry her.
Even if people who claim to have objective knowledge of us
tell me over and over again, it will be a disaster.
I am going to marry her based on my feelings,
Based on the X.
experience I have when I'm with her.
But the way you actually should pick the girl
you're gonna marry is,
it includes both of those.
It's not a rejection of either of those.
It includes both of those.
It includes those actual factual considerations
on the one hand, and it includes how you feel
you're with her and you're love for her right?
including romantic love is modern and ideas that is on the other side.
Those things are included.
But it brings those two things together and then surpasses them with something else.
With something else. I think the same is true with the church.
On one side you've got the factual considerations, apostolic succession, history,
tradition, unbroken, right, et cetera.
etc., etc., historic church, going back to the apostles, all of that, right?
And books about it, right? On the other side, you've got, here's the experience I have in worship.
Right? Here's how, here's how I feel. Here's it, right? But the reason to choose to be a part of the church
brings both of those together and then surpasses it. And that thing that surpasses it
is an encounter with Christ. And what does that mean?
Right? I can't define exactly what that means to encounter Christ, even though I believe I had
it happen. Any more than I can define what it was that made me know I should marry my wife,
Christian. And that happened to me, too. Right? But that doesn't mean it's not real,
the fact that I can't define it or fully describe it.
And I tell every inquirer
in every category of human who comes into my parish.
That there are a lot of reasons why people join the Orthodox Church, but there's only
one good one.
And that's that you have that encounter with Christ.
That brings together those two elements and then supersedes them.
If you don't have that in my parish, you should not join my parish.
And if you do, then you should.
like if you don't have that with a woman you shouldn't marry her.
But if you do, then you should.
Does that make sense, even though it's not something you can totally define, there's an
ineffable quality to it, which you would expect.
Yeah, you said God.
Exactly. That is what I was getting at with my...it's so unsatisfactory, I think it must be right.
That has been often my experience with God has been, you'll know, and I hate that answer.
But it's next.
I think it's true when I, the other thing is I was already kind of leaning that direction.
So the fact that these two answers, both of your answers have kind of come together into this.
Yeah, you'll know.
I think that's probably my answer, but I will say just to sort of add on to both of those
that I think I could see both of those extremes, if you want to call them, that leading towards
the center. Those are just two prongs that can kind of catch people who go and either
either to the intellectual or the sentimental.
And I do both at different times.
And it has been really satisfied in both of those ways
with the Orthodox Church so far.
So, yeah, I'll certainly keep exploring, but I appreciate the answers.
And just in general, I really appreciate the show
and the way you two approach these things.
It's been profoundly helpful with a number of issues forming.
So yeah, I think it's taken the time, brothers.
Thank God. Thank God.
Alright.
Well, the third half, what do we do with all this stuff?
I don't know now.
What then show we do?
Yeah, stuck like a joke, we're out of luck.
So yeah, so well, what's supposed to be a reactionary father's
team?
I mean, that seems like the thing to do.
What response to this is you look at modernism and post-wires and you look at all these
currents and you just become a reactionary.
You just react to it.
Yeah.
Right? And this of course we talked we mentioned this back in the very first half that
Like the fundamentalists responding to the modernists
When you become a reactionary you tend to end up assuming what you claim to hate
Right you stare to the abyss of the abyss tears back into you
So you know
uh
I hate postmodernism that I hate post
Christian worship. So I am going to, you know, loudly assert my opinion that we
ought to do it this other way and very forcefully. Or I'm going to go try and get a
bunch of people to agree with me by giving them really convincing arguments and
then we're going to come and we're going to change it. Right in the church. And it's
like, oh, whoops, right, you're doing the exact same thing. Right in your
reaction and it can get even
worse, right? Because you could do things like, for example, if you're reacting against
modernism and modern egalitarianism, you could say, well, okay, you're trying to historicize
all these hierarchies. I'm going to naturalize them all. Yeah. Right? I'm going to say, no,
the people on the top are on top because they deserve to be on the top. They were born to be
on the top. God put them on top and the people on the bottom were there because they deserve to be
down on the bottom and now we'll send you back to the pagan view of human nature.
it's literally pagan as like the sense of audit excellence, you know?
Yeah, you're you're you're you're there with either Nietzsche or the Roman Empire before it was Christian. Right. Congratulations.
Yeah. But you've you've left Christianity in the other direction. Right.
You've overshot.
And you can become a reactionary, you start engaging in sort of selective totalitarianism.
Right, we need to, we need an authoritarian leader
to clean all this stuff up.
And as long as I get to choose who the dictator is,
that'll be fine.
I know.
Right, which is like by definition,
you don't elect dictators, right?
That's not how it works.
It'll be our dictator.
Yeah.
Or you get a kind of like we've talked about
with a lot of trads.
You get this selective traditionalism.
where I'm making my own recons, instead of me making some liberalized, egalitarian,
reconstruction of early Christianity, I'm making my own trad reconstruction of Christianity
that may or may not accord with any actual Christianity that's existed in the real world.
It could be one from Colomé, one from Colombe.
My favorite version of that that I actually saw, and I was like, that can't be real, but
But then I was reading it, it was real.
Was someone who...
So convinced that we are living in the time of Antichrist, setting aside, of course, the issue that St. John
told us that Antichrist is plural and that he was living in the time of an Antichrist.
You know, it's lots of them. He said that the ecclesiology of St. Ignatius of Antioch, which you've
ever, you know, kids, if you've ever read St. Ignatius, you know he has a whole lot to say about the
authority of the bishop that the ecclesiology of synagnetias of Antioch.
doesn't apply anymore because we're living in the time of anti-Christ. I'm like,
St. Ignatius was living in the time of anti-Christ, but it's a selective traditionalism.
Like, I really like this, but when there's some guy with a big title or big hat,
telling me what to do, forget that nonsense.
Wherever the church fathers agree with me, they're important.
Wherever they disagree with me, yeah, what do they know?
Yeah.
Yeah, you get this very selective pick and choose
and then make your own tradition.
Right?
And the overall problem though,
with being a reactionary,
and in addition to everything we just listed,
is that you can't actually de-innovate.
You can't actually go back to being a pre-modern person.
Yeah, I mean, even share saying,
if I could turn back time,
but she knows that she can't.
Right, and so this is that danger I mentioned.
This is that daydream I mentioned within conservatism of sliding into postmodernism.
Because you approach a modernist liberal, there you're opponent, right?
You think you're going to reject modernity and go back to pre-modernity, but what actually
happens is you reject modernity and become postmodern.
Because you can't become pre-modern.
You can't put the toothpaste back in the...
the tube. Right. And so you just slide into a postmodern version of conservatism that
is just as divorced from historic Christianity as any postmodern left position as any modernist
liberal position, right, you divorced yourself from Christianity. So what then is the
response.
Right? We can't roll the clock back. Right?
The answer is the continuity that we were talking about in the last couple of episodes, which
requires you to be grounded in an actual living tradition.
A tradition that's alive today that is functioning, meaning it's functioning and alive in a community.
So you're not reconstructing anything, right?
It's there and it exists.
And it has exists and it has this continuity stretching backwards into the past.
And you ground yourself within that tradition. And then once you're grounded in that tradition
and you're formed by the tradition which doesn't happen immediately. You have to allow the tradition
to form you, you have to submit to it. It takes time, it takes obedience, it takes.
Yeah, I don't know what I'm doing. You know what you're doing. I'm going to do what you tell me to do.
But as that happened
As we submit to that and we're shaped by the tradition, then we're able to recognize,
right, we're able to recognize, for example, what is just a change like we put in parking lots
because now people drive cars, right, but not an actual break in the continuity of tradition,
versus what is a break in the continuity with tradition.
Yeah.
Right.
With what is actually allowing some foreign elements, something from outs.
side of Christianity, outside of the living Christian tradition to come in and twist it,
and reshape it.
You become familiar with the edges of the tradition as you're formed and shaped by it.
And so there are times when there are changes within the church, within given person's lifetime,
or something.
something that changes, something that is different.
Right?
But it is in complete continuity with the past.
It is a native development, not something foreign coming in.
So for example, the 20th century in the Orthodox Church, there was a return to people receiving
more frequent communion.
Yeah, and I mean, that was a return after, as far as we know, centuries.
Input to receive the ugr is very infrequent.
in most parts of the Orthodox world.
And this is not something that was started by Western converts.
No.
There's a movement that happened within Orthodox countries.
Yeah.
In the Orthodox world.
And in different places at the same time, interestingly.
Yeah.
It was a revitalizing agreement.
Now, for the person who was alive at that time, that was a change.
Yeah.
It seemed weird.
they had to look at it, they had to decide, okay is this...
Is this a native, is this a shift, is this a native thing that's native to the Christian tradition, which it was ultimately, right?
That needs to be accepted, or is this a break?
Is this some foreign thing coming in and influencing us and trying to change Christianity, right?
Which it wasn't.
as an aside. Okay. I know there's somebody out there. In fact, I probably know who it is.
Who's going, what about metamotornism?
I read about that on the interwebs.
What about metamotornism?
Metamotornism is not a thing.
Okay, it's like streets ahead.
It's not a thing.
You can't make it a thing.
Okay.
If you go and try and research what metamotornism is,
what you'll find on the internet is,
Will this guy uses metamotorism to mean to know?
This other guy uses it to be something totally different.
So this is a term people are trying to use and define.
You forget about it. It's not a thing.
You can't really define social movements while they're going on.
You define them in retrospect.
So we were really understanding what postmodernism was like in the 90s.
But it was happening in the 60s and 70s and 80s.
Yeah, right. So if...
there is some other post post modern period going on right now.
10, 15, 20 years from now, we'll have a good label for it and we'll be able to define it.
But this is not going to offer this better modernism stuff until that.
I mean, I really do feel like the moment we're in at the moment, yeah.
It's still pretty pretty post modern, you know, because there's so much,
You know, assertions of identity and all this kind of...
There's so much of that right now.
But there'll be a backlash against it.
And that'll be something who knows.
But you could have a backlash that's just as post-water.
So yeah, so,
from my perspective,
I hazard to get's probably also from Father Andrews.
The Orthodox Church has a
way of bridging a lot of these issues. For example, the universal in the particular. So the
Orthodox Church is the church, it is universal. It is the one who like Catholic and Apostolic
Church. Don't apologize for that. But it is constituted by particular local churches.
from different cultures,
the worship in different languages,
who have their own sub-traditions
that are part of the whole.
Right?
And then also, ultimately,
it's made up of particular parishes.
One of the other things I tell inquires
and catacumans that my parish is
you don't join the Orthodox Church,
you join N Orthodox Church.
Yeah, this Orthodox Church is a community.
Because
you're a member of N Orthodox Church, you are a member of the Orthodox Church, right?
Which is the communion of all of those churches, all those communities, right?
And so the universal and the particular are there brought together, right?
The Orthodox Church bridges subjectivity and reality because there is definitely a role
for religious experience, right?
that I'm sure it's not completely rationalistic.
but there's also a belief in a concrete reality.
Everything is not up for grabs.
Yeah, just because you,
just because you perceive something
doesn't mean that it's not in any way subject to
speaking with your spiritual father, being examined,
being interpreted, critiqued, whatever.
That subjectivity is embraced, but is correctable.
Yeah.
And that's we.
because it offers an experience that is concrete.
Right, what does that mean?
That means that there is an experience of Christ,
when I was just talking about with the caller,
that has been shared by people,
frankly for as long as there have been humans.
Right, when he walked in the garden with Adam and Eve,
right, those primitive hunter-gatherers
who were gauging a true worship of the true God
an encounter with Christ.
Abraham saw him, all the way through. He appeared in the temple on the day of
atonement. He was in Karnet, died, rose again, ascended into heaven, appeared at
least three times to St. Paul, on and on and on. There's this experience, appeared
in his uncreated glory to the saints. There's this experience of Christ,
There's this constant all the way down, right? That is ineffable to a certain extent.
But, describable enough in its contours that we can talk about continuity, right?
Within the tradition that's been handed down.
So that if I feel like I've had an experience of Christ, and it doesn't conform to that
experience of Christ which has gone on throughout human history, then I know that mine is incorrect,
I'm incorrect that maybe it wasn't an experience of Christ or maybe I misinterpreted that experience.
experience. Right? That makes it correctable. That makes it
critiquable. In other Christian circles, if someone comes to you, it says, the Holy
Spirit told me X, that's not critiquable. Yeah. Can't say no, he didn't. Right? So,
Again, there is this kind of direct spiritual experience.
Right. This is orthodoxy is not a cessationist religion where you know people used to have
visions and used things, but now that we now we kind of don't we just you know go about
our business, right? And a mostly material world, right? No. Right. But it's also isn't the
wild west of spirituality, right? Of just whatever impression I have, you know, is unquestionable,
Right, and it's true for me.
same time we have to be honest about the Orthodox Church, Father Andrew and I, right?
So these things we were talking about, right, you will run into people in Orthodox
churches. You will run into liberals. Yeah. There's theological liberals. You'll run into
people trying to remake the Orthodox Church. Yeah. But they're getting it. But they're
try. No, there's literally, yeah, by the way, if any of those
people are listening, there's literally no mechanism by which the kinds of changes
you want can happen. It can't. It's not in place. You'll find your, especially among
the catacuminent, you'll find your reactionaries. You'll find them. I mean, welcome. Welcome.
you'll find, hey we've all got work to do, right?
Right, yeah, we're not throwing these people out.
No, bye.
None of them, right?
You'll find plenty of people who are post-modern, as I'll get out, right?
Wandered around in Orthodox churches, right? Some of them were born there.
Some of them came in, some of them were in the process of coming in, right? You see you'll find all this.
It's not that, you know,
we are a church that produces saints, but we're not all saints, especially me, right?
and
these things are and beyond just finding folks who are in the grips of those ideologies,
they are, right, ideologies remember our spirits, right? They are after the church. That's
not, it's not that, you know, you're going to join the Orthodox Church, it just be like,
Okay, well now I never have to worry about liberalism or post-modernism erectionaries again.
None of these cultural currents will ever affect me again now that I have joined the orthodox
shirt.
There's people who come and that's there, they think that that's the case.
They're going to escape from all that.
That's not the case.
That's not reality.
And there are even, you know, some of the temptations, like we talked about the temptation
in evangelicalism, the way a swath of evangelicalism has gone into postmodernism and how, you know,
mainline liberalism
has just gone down the modernism route.
And we said that those who go down those roads,
I'll put this plane, aren't properly speaking Christians,
so not practicing Christianity.
Once you go down that road far enough, right?
It is something other than Christianity.
But, and those two may not be big temptations
in the Orthodox Church as a whole, but we have our own,
We have our own stuff.
Like for example, I mentioned we have local churches, right?
And a lot of those local churches are national churches.
And guess what?
One of the big temptations we face is nationalism.
Yeah.
Where the lines get blurry, you know?
And what's the difference?
Well, it's the same as all the other things we've been talking about, right?
The church in a given nation should be transforming that nation.
with Orthodox Christianity. But it happens, it happens, right? In times and places,
not the whole church, not even part of the church permanently, but there are
times and places where parts of the church end up getting influenced by the
nation more than their influencing the nation. Yeah, it gets transformed in
in the wrong the transfer agent goes in the wrong direction.
in the wrong direction. Yeah, you know, it just is big of a problem when that happens as any of
the other problems we've talked about tonight. Yeah, and you can get, I mean, some of the most
the worst results of that is you can get imperialism. Yeah, orthodox nations have been imperialists.
You can get cultural shauvinism. You know, these things absolutely have racism. Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, you know, and it does.
make it any less bad just because it's quote-unquote orthodox. Right. Right. So never let it be said
that we're not self-critical. Right. We have our problems too. They may not always be the same
problems, but we have problems. Right. We have orthodox church. We have struggles. We have
temptations. We have these things we have to deal with. That last bit about national churches
and nationalists, frankly, I know I've talked about the show before. This is why I'm so down on the
the idea of an American Orthodox Church.
It was a dream of Metropolitan Philip of Thrice Blessed Memory that he and his lifetime,
which didn't happen, would see United American Orthodox Church with respect to his eminence.
I'm glad it didn't happen, and I hope it doesn't happen while I'm still alive.
Because right now, the way American culture and society is, and as weak and small as Orthodox
Christianity is in the United States,
the influence.
will only go one way if there's an American Orthodox Church. And that will be American culture
coming in and deforming the Orthodox faith. Yeah, I think we have now, if it happened today,
we have so much work to do in terms of being more Christian, you know, and I know some
people think they're like, well, we could do that better if we had this. But it's like,
There's nothing stopping you from doing it right now.
decade I've been approached by more people in different churches who tell me that
their biggest problem and the reason why they may stop going to church is that
there are people from the other political party going to that church. Yeah.
That tells you everything you need to know an American Orthodox church would be
a disaster. People can't even set aside their political party to worship Christ
to as the king.
of everything. Right? We're not ready. Sorry, everybody. But it's reality. Face it. Okay?
We need a couple hundred more years. We need to grow a lot. We need to make
America Orthodox. And then we could have an American Orthodoxy. Frankly, this is
what needs to happen. And it's going to take us a while to make America Orthodox.
So get to work. But it's not the goal of your lifetime. You got a lot of work to do.
It's not the goal in any event.
I mean it's...
not the goal. That's not the goal. It might be a tool that helps us towards the goal,
which is, you know, to become saints, to become to be Christians. That's the goal.
You know, yeah. Right. Go out there. If you want to see it in your lifetime, go out there and
become equal to the apostles in converting the United States of America to Orthodox Christianity.
There's your job description. If you successfully do that in your lifetime, it may happen in your
I don't have to.
Well, I'm working on it, but it's not going to happen in my life, but I'm pretty sure.
Pretty sure.
Never know, but probably not.
So, yeah, I know that this episode, so just, you know, some wrap up thoughts.
I know that this episode, I mean, literally pretty philosophical at points, although, honestly,
I mean, we, it was mostly overview in a lot of ways, a lot of, a lot of these ideas.
which is probably about the most that most of us can take,
including me, most of the time.
Despite my forays into reading Terry Eagleton.
But I think that for me,
the big takeaway of a lot of this
is number one, even though maybe at moments like this, we can step back and see big swaths of history and say,
Oh, so that's what the problem with everything is.
We still are where we are.
You know, I think of that poem by Tennis, and I think it's called Ulysses, where he says,
you know, I'm probably, I'm probably, I'm just remembering some of the lines, but, you know,
essentially, you know, even though we don't have that strength that we had in olden days, we are what we are.
What we are, we are, I think that's the line.
Um.
And I think that that's an important thing to remember, not so we can just throw our hands up and say,
well, there's nothing to be done. But rather just to take it in humility, say, okay, I'm a modern person,
living the modern period. I see the problems of modernism, or at least some of them. And I'm gonna
to stumble forward, trying not to fall in any of the ditches that I'm surrounded by.
I think one of the big temptations is to think that we're special in that we have big
struggles like this.
But we're not.
Every historical era and every historical place has its problems, has its big temptations.
And we know that people go careening off onto the wrong paths.
And we know.
that in the midst of those situations, that people become holy, that people become
sons of God. You know, there is no gold in era. And yeah, it's true, we're not in it.
But there isn't one. There were certain points where maybe the material situation
and the church was much better.
But that doesn't mean that conditions for being saved were better.
Doesn't mean that.
For me, if we're going to look to any era of church history
and find inspiration, first, I mean, all of them, right? There's saints in all the
eras of church history, and we can find inspiration from all of those saints in various ways.
but if there's one I'm gonna pick it.
And say this is the one that I think we need to hold up first.
That doesn't mean we don't hold up the other ones ever.
But the one we need to hold up first is the first one, is the Apostolic period, where the
apostles are going out into all the world preaching the gospel, baptizing the name of the father,
son and Holy Spirit, and making disciples of every creature and teaching them to do all
that Christ commanded them.
And it just so happens, I believe, that our current era, while not the same in some pretty
big important ways, in many ways because of this post-modern cultural meadow we're in
now, I think is much like the time of the Apostles.
It was a very polyreligious period with a lot of cross-currents, a lot going on, a lot of
directions to
move in, you know, it's not the modern world where you pick, you pick a religion. It's
not that, but nonetheless, there was a lot to be confused by and a lot to, to draw the
eye and a lot to draw desire. And frankly, a lot of, a lot of real decadence and material
gluttony of various kinds. We have all of that.
And the apostles went out without any expectation that they were going to be successful in their culture.
They went out and obeyed what God told them to do.
They went out and they preached the gospel to people.
And anyone who listened, anyone who said, yes, I'm on board with that.
How do I be saved?
They baptized them. They taught them how to be faithful.
And then the next generation received that and they
They passed it on and they passed it on and on and on down to us the littlest and least
of the brothers and sisters of the Christian story.
So I mean, for me, whenever I hear even some very depressing stuff we talked about and
I think like, I mean, there's points when we were talking about the privileging of experience,
right?
I know that when I've talked about Orthodox Christianity with people over the last few decades.
I know I've made appeals to experience sometimes for people.
And I also know like how problematic that is.
But I also know like appeals to the more kind
of intellectual approach and also how problematic that is.
But nonetheless, I have hope because it's not me who
who is really giving them Christ.
And...
It's not even truly themselves who are discovering Christ.
It's Christ who has come to look for us.
And the way that he meets each person, the way that each person encounters him,
is going to be different and mysterious and particular to them.
but participating in the common experience of Christ that the Church has.
And then it's not only that initial experience,
then it's an ongoing experience
and receiving from other people within the church,
their experience as well,
and receiving all of these things together.
I mean, this is how a tradition works.
It's this river running through history
that has all of the church in it.
And so for me, it always comes down to hope.
And it's not hope like, well, I hope that happens,
but it's just fundamental.
upward gazing hope where we see Christ and even though there's going to be stones on the road
and ruts to fall into, we step forward, we stumble forward and we give thanks along the way.
So that's what I have to say.
I guess upward gazing is better than naval gazing or shoe gazing
of the available gazing options.
So, yeah, so this is sort of, this episode, we sort of did an episode that turned into a
two-part series that then turned into a three-part series.
And I think both where we started and where we ended up are very germane to the whole
race on debt of the show, because this, this show is just a Bible show, right?
There is undead of the show from the beginning.
has been that we're trying to re-acquire some of the wisdom that was lost in the movement
into modernism where we gained this incredible knowledge of science and technology, which
is all real knowledge. But we lost the spiritual wisdom that maybe we had before in trying
to recover that. So, discussing what modernism is is very germane. As is talking about the
spiritual experience of Neil
with a countergatherer, which is where we started out two episodes ago.
But mainly the last couple episodes, what we've been talking about is
this contrast between Christianity, between the church, as it exists in the world,
and that Christianity being a transformative influence on the world,
in which it exists, verse.
is that Christianity being twisted and deformed by the world in which it exists and turned into
something different by these foreign elements that come and intrude. And what we've been saying
about church communities applies just as much to me as a person. So we've talked about, and we
We talked about tonight that my identity is a person.
is not as an individual and it's not some ever shifting protean self either but
it is the sort of stacked up and meshed web of relationships that I exist in. I'm a
priest, I'm the pastor of a parish, I'm a husband, I'm a spiritual father, I'm a
brother. I'm a son. I'm an uncle. I'm a great uncle.
I'm a friend to certain people.
I'm an acquaintance of certain other people.
I'm a writer of books, which is a certain kind of relationship with readers.
Make this podcast. It's a certain type of relationship with listeners.
All of these things make up my identity.
Basically, I'm an Orthodox Christian within that.
But I can choose
And I have to choose, and more than choosing, it's not just a question of making choices,
often it feels more like a struggle or a fight.
One way or the other.
To allow my Orthodox Christian identity,
to be sort of subsumed, to be shifted, to be conditioned,
to be warped.
to minister by the world I live in with all of its modern and postmodern currents, or I can
choose to live in a way and to struggle in a way in which by Orthodox Christianity and
by that I essentially mean the presence of the Holy Spirit within me. Allow that to transform
me. And then three.
transforming me through that web of relationships begin to transform the world
around me. There is no kind of middle ground there. There is no kind of middle
point. There's no homeostasis where you can just relax and now you know
everything's okay and you can go about your business. Back to my hobbies I've
got that whole Christianity thing covered. One of those two things will
be happening. We'll be being shaped by one or the other. We'll be being shaped by the
Holy Spirit as a person, or we'll be being shaped by the various spirits that are active
in our world, the zeitgeists that are out there, pushing at us and wanting to lead us
in other directions. The promise that the Holy Spirit has is that the transformation
that the Holy Spirit offers.
To the Christian, to the Christian New Struggles, Struggles with Repentance.
Struggles to do good, Struggles to bring forth the fruit of the Spirit.
We've got a tender garden, get a tender orchard for it to bring forth fruit.
These, as I said, not only that we would be transformed by it,
but that through the web of relationships that connect us to those around us,
Connect us to our world.
that our world and those other people would be transformed.
It's kind of a chain reaction.
This is what St. Sarah from the Sarah was talking about in the famous quote,
acquired the Holy Spirit.
Thousands will be saved all around you.
That is our task.
And so I hope, and that's why I put it here at the very end, right,
Right, the people's take...
away, everything we had to say about the church, its society, and history, and religion,
and these episodes, as it developed, changed where there were breaks, cottons, discontinues,
over time, throughout human history.
All of that is good stuff from my perspective.
I think all that's important.
That's why we did the episodes.
But if we don't take that and apply it to our own day to day way of life, our own...
day to day struggle. To be a St. Paul says in the world, but not of the world. To be shaping
the world, not being shaped by it. If we don't apply that, then this is so much abstract
formulation. It's knowledge that puffs up. We could think, I understand all of these
currents in our culture, but it won't actually profit us anything.
So we need to...
be struggling harder in our own life against foreign ideas, foreign ideologies and intruders.
Then we do against those intruders in our church.
God will take care of those intruders in our church.
Bishops will take care of those intruders in our church.
If we take care of those intrusions,
in our own life through that web of relationships,
that will help take care of those intruders in our church.
So if we're talking about intruders that aren't human,
if we're talking about spirits,
those get cast out.
If we're talking about people coming into our churches
who are moved by those spirits,
then when those spirits get cast out,
transforms transform our quote unquote enemies into.
friends. That's part of that transformation too. That's why we don't throw out our liberals.
That's why we don't throw out our reactionaries. That's why we don't throw out our post-modernists.
Right? Because I'm one of those somewhere in there as me, right? Or at least was. Hopefully
more was than is.
And that transformation is transforming us all together.
So it's summary, yes.
Hopefully if you've listened to this, don't just try to apply it to the Neolithic era.
Don't just try to apply it to your understanding of what's going on in evangelicalism.
But first and foremost, try and apply it to yourself as I try to apply it to myself.
Man
Amen. Well, in two weeks we'll be our annual Halloween episode. But that's all our
show is for tonight. So thank you for listening. If you didn't get through to this live, we'd
select to hear from you. You can email us at Lord of Spirit at ancient fate.com. You can
message us at our Facebook page or leave us a voice mail at speakpipe.com slash Lord
of Spirits. You have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help finding
a parish head over to orthodoxintro.org.
Enjoy this for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursday.
days of the month at 7 PM Eastern 4 PM Pacific, dream of better lives, the kind which never
hate trapped in this state of imaginary grace.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews
and ratings in all the appropriate places, most importantly, share this show with a friend
who's going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to AncientFate.com, Stroke Support, and help make sure we and lots
of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
I made a pilgrimage to save the human race, ever comprehending the race at Long Gone
Thank you, good night, and may God bless you.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I be held and I heard the voice of many angels.
about the throne and the beasts and the elders.
And the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice,
worthy as the land that was slain to receive power
and riches and wisdom and strength and honor
and glory and blessing.
Revelation.